<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The quæstion of tythes reuised Arguments for the moralitie of tything, enlarged, and cleared. Obiections more fully, and distinctly answered .Mr. Seldens historie, so farre as mistakers haue made it argumentatiue against the moralitie, ouer-ly viewed. By William Sclater, D.D. and minister of Pitmister, in Somerset.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835902</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835902</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11601)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The quæstion of tythes reuised Arguments for the moralitie of tything, enlarged, and cleared. Obiections more fully, and distinctly answered .Mr. Seldens historie, so farre as mistakers haue made it argumentatiue against the moralitie, ouer-ly viewed. By William Sclater, D.D. and minister of Pitmister, in Somerset.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 33, [6], 34-35, [6], 36-59, 72-226, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The ministers portion.</note>
                  <note>"Though this has the headline: "The ministers portion", this is a different work from STC 21841, published in 1612."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Selden, John, 1584-1654. --  Historie of tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Quaeſtion of TYTHES REVISED.</p>
            <p>ARGVMENTS FOR THE Moralitie of Tything, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and cleared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OBIECTIONS MORE fully, and diſtinctly anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> SELDENS Hiſtorie, ſo farre as <hi>Mistakers haue made it</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentatiue againſt the Moralitie, <hi>ouer-ly viewed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER, D. D. and Miniſter of <hi>Pitmister,</hi> in <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEVT. 33. Verſe 10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Of <hi>Leui</hi> he ſaid, They ſhall teach <hi>Iacob</hi> thy Iudgements, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> thy Law.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe, O Lord, his ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands: Smile through the loynes of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN LEGATT. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REVERENDO IN CHRISTO PATRI AC DOMINO, ARTHVRO, Prouidentia Diuinâ Bathonienſi ac Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſi Epiſcopo, Domino meo plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimùm obſeruando.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorande Praeſul, Annus iam agitur fermè duodecimus, ex quo mea, qualiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque, de Iure Decimarum velitatio, in vulgus emanauit. Quanto, Credis, cum literatorum propè omnium ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſu? Nec tamen ſine vulgi (abſit verbo inuidia) Sacrilegi oblatratu. Fremerè exin atque indignari quotquot in Sacra inuolarant, non aliter ac Demetrius Epheſinus cum ſuis, vbi Dianae magnificen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia periclitaretur, hoc eſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> illorum in diſcrimen vergeret. Nimirum &amp; de Arte Decimandi, perinde vt de Statuaria Opifices illi, Generoſi fere omnes noſtri ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter victitant.</p>
            <p>Siquis paulò cordatior, vacillare aliquantulum, vt fit, &amp; tremere: mox etiam gratulari ſibi, quòd de Rure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno, non de Iure Paſtoritio victum ſibi quaeritaret. Mirari Ego quorſum Res exiret: Cum ecce Conductitius neſcio quis, Decimarum &amp; ipſe, quod nunc audio, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Heluo, mea omnia ventilare, ſugillare; cenſura ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra quàm Magistrali luſtrare; ſcommate vere Lucianico
<pb facs="tcp:133:3"/> mordere, rodere: Pedum etiam ſupploſioni, ſi fas, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere. Tranſacta Res eſt: verſa, euerſa ſunt omnia: Sopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt denuo Conſcientia. Faxit Deus, ne non &amp; mortua.</p>
            <p>Eam ego vt ſemiſepultam, ſi pote, exuſcitem, id vero nunc do operam, quàm vereor, ne non inanem? vt, vt, Accepta ſit Deo, Eccleſiae vtilis, Tibi grata, Sat habeo. Inhient etiamdum plenis faucibus Heliogabali nostri Peculio Dei: vorent quod ſacrum eſt &amp; ſanctum Deo. Vorent, vt euomant. Quis vero ferat niſi <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> perire Sacrilegos? Subit etiam mentem, &amp; ſolatur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantulum, quod Iudeis diuerbti loco dicitur, Quando duplicantur lateres, tunc venit Moſes. Hac ſpe (quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla?) fretus, Rem ipſam aggredior; Auſpicato, credo, ſatis, quod ſub tuis Tanti viri, Auſpiciis. Soſpitet Deus.</p>
            <p>Quod ſupereſt Deum Optimum Maximum enixe comprecor, vt Amplitudinem tuam indies magis magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que amplam reddat: Ipſum Te Eccleſiae, Nobis, quàm diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimè incolumem ſeruet: vt, quod facis, Pietate, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, Industria, Clero tuo praeluceas. Faxit. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Pitmiſterij,</hi> Dat. <date>
                     <hi>Kalendis Ianuarijs, Anno Reparationis humanae 1621.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Amplitudinis tuae ſtudioſiſsimus, Idem qui &amp; Capellanus tibi addictiſsimus, <hi>WILL. SCLATER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:133:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I began to ſmatter in <hi>iudgement</hi> of queſtions, thus I haue euer thought of the particular; that its amongſt thoſe, that may much more eaſily be <hi>defended,</hi> then <hi>eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</hi> So vtterly inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiall, are all arguments pretended againſt the diuine right of Tything, yet ſo blind is preiudice, ſo eareleſſe the belly, ſo ſtiffe and abſurd couetouſneſſe, in denying principles, and in ſpight of all premiſes reſolued to hold the concluſion of Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>Difficultie of euiction ariſeth hence: firſt, that <hi>oppoſites take from vs appearing principles, and put vs to prooue them in our owne ſcience:</hi> ſecondly, haue framed to themſelues principles, which no man muſt dare to contradict, vnder perill of hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at for abſurditie: A principle it ſeemes to my poore vnderſtanding. Firſt, that praecepts of God, neuer ſo ancient, hauing no appearing repeale, binde euer to the end of the world.
<pb facs="tcp:133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Secondly, that men willing to looſe Conſcience from bond of any diuine praecept, ſuch eſpecially as but lookes towards moralitie, muſt be able to ſhew, by ſoundeſt euidence, the abrogating of that, from which they pretend to be inlarged. For what our Sauiour diſclaimes, dares any attempt?<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Diſſoluing the Law in any Iot or title?</hi> without cleare ſignification of the Law-giuers will for ceſſation? Or ſuppoſe wee, hee ſpeakes of the maine only after the letter, and not of particulars, and degrees of dutie, couched vnder the maine? Of particulars and degrees of ſinne implyed in the groſſe? who ſhould not tremble at ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane arrogancie, that heares him proteſt <hi>his</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>nullitie in Gods kingdome, who breakes, or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth breach of the leſt commandement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis ſtrange libertie theſe licentious times haue taken; to cancell at pleaſure, what their fancie diſtaſteth in the Law of God.</p>
            <p>How vrgent is the<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 4.15, 6.</note> 
               <hi>caueat against Image ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> for repreſentation, or worſhip of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; how plentifully particularized, and backt with reaſons? yet goes it for current doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome Papiſts, that the praecept was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie, peculiar to Iewes; in reſpect of their groſſe rudeneſſe, and ſtrong propenſion to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Its a praecept in <hi>caſu,</hi> to<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſweare the Lord liueth in truth, in iudgement, and in righteouſneſſe.</hi> A toleration rather, ſay Anabaptiſts, limited to Iewes, in their eſtate of weakeneſſe, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. No oath lawfull to Chriſtians in new
<pb facs="tcp:133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Teſtament, in what cauſe ſoeuer, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ſoeuer impoſed.</p>
            <p>Praecept of Sabbath, ancient, ſome thinke, as the world for the <hi>quota</hi> of time; we are ſure, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled by Gods owne finger in the two Tables of ſtone; yet thought a meere Iewiſh ceremonie, to vaniſh with other ſhadows of heauenly things, in this time of reformation.</p>
            <p>Subiection to Chriſtian Magiſtrates, inioyned<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>in the first commandement with promiſe,</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Anabaptiſts make proper to the State, and politie of ruder Iewes.</p>
            <p>Vſury, ſo damned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Prophets, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Churches, Heathens, is deemed a ſinne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar only to the people of Iewes.</p>
            <p>Were <hi>Nicholas</hi> of Antioch now aliue; or <hi>Nichols</hi> the Familiſt, approaching as neere to his hereſie, as to his name; they would voyce it as ſtrongly, that fornication was a ſinne peculiar to Iewes; And that Chriſtians may liue after the licence of <hi>Plato</hi> his Common-wealth, rather then aſtrict themſelues to theſe lawes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> made ſeuerall, as their opinion ſeemes, to the Iewiſh Nation.</p>
            <p>May not <hi>Dauids</hi> Apoſtrophe beſeeme vs in theſe times,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 119.126.</note> 
               <hi>Its time for thee, Lord, to lay to thy hand, for men haue deſtroyed thy Law.</hi> What praecept, with greateſt inſtance preſſed, may not a licentious Libertine plead to bee exempted from? If it may be lawfull, without ground to auouch it meerely Iudaicall? Yea, how would
<pb facs="tcp:133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> my ſoule wiſh rather to be a Iew, that diſſolute nature might be reſtrayned in mee by lawes, and my Conſcience inioy the ſweete comforts found in obedience, then to inioy ſuch liberties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſuch lawleſſe licence, to be Idolatrous, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urious, impious, Sacrilegious?</p>
            <p>Should not Chriſtian Conſcience be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, how it ſlights any the praecepts of God? Had not the euidences need be praegnant, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs to beleeue our freedome from their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>Thinke of it ſeriouſly, you that put vs to plead our <hi>ius,</hi> while you keepe poſſeſsion of Tythes: whither it lye not rather on your Conſcience, to prooue repeale of that diuine Law-giuen for Tything. Leaſt that taxe of our Sauiour laid on the Phariſees, light on you; <hi>full well haue you</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Math. 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>abrogated Gods commandement to ſtabliſh your owne tradition,</hi> or rather fancy. And<note n="h" place="margin">Iude 12.</note> 
               <hi>without feare to feed</hi> your owne couetouſneſſe, and luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with Gods reſerued portion. Once wee are ſure, a law of Tything there was giuen of God: obſerued by Patriarches, ancient Iewes, and Chriſtians; maintained by Fathers, to ſtand ſtill in force: how may any dare auouch it abrogated without cleareſt euidence of the word of God?</p>
            <p>Their principles, ſuch as they are, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued amongſt the <hi>vulgus</hi> and their Chaplens, let vs examine. 1. That is impregnable borrowed from Manichees, pointed at by <hi>Thomas;</hi> that <hi>Christians ſtand bound to no praecept of Moſes, or
<pb facs="tcp:133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Prophets, which Chriſt, or his Apostles haue not, in Scriptures of New Teſtament, giuen life vnto.</hi> Would they, I trow, be ſo vnderſtood? that all Moſaicall; and Propheticall praecepts, which are not <hi>totidem verbis</hi> reuiued in new Teſtament; are now <hi>mortua? Apageſis Antinome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſufficeth the proteſtation of our Sauiour that he<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>came not to deſtroy the leſt title of</hi> Moſes <hi>his morall Law;</hi> and that of <hi>Paul,</hi> that<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 3.31.</note> 
               <hi>faith doth not abrogate the Law, but rather ſtabliſh it,</hi> to countenance whatſoeuer Law giuen by <hi>Moſes,</hi> explicated by Prophets, which was not either particularly iudiciall, or amongſt the ſhadowes of things to come. That yeelded, till that of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be euidenced to bee amongſt the ſeuerals of the Iewes, life it hath ſufficient put into it by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in their proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and auouchment for the generall.</p>
            <p>But who ſo is acquainted with their diſcreeteſt anſwers to arguments grounded on Scriptures of the new Teſtament, ſhall finde them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a praecept, punctually there ſpeaking for Tythes; with ſuch ſcorne ſhall hee heare argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of moſt apparent conſequence thence drawne, reiected; becauſe the concluſion for Tythes, <hi>vnder that name,</hi> is not extant in our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>Make the inſtructer partaker of all thy goods,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle. Part-taker, ſaid an Arch-preſbyter amongſt them, not Tenth-taker; and pleaſed himſelfe much in the elegance.<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>As Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui miniſtring about holy things, liues of the Temple,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp;c. <hi>So hath Chriſt ordained for them that preach the Goſpel, to liue of the Goſpel.</hi> To liue of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, God forbid elſe; but had <hi>Paul</hi> meant Tythes, doubtleſſe hee would haue named them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their ſecond Principle then is this, that Scriptures of new Teſtament meane to oblige vs to no duty, but what by name it commends vnto vs. Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, I thinke, and our lay-Parſons, are, in the grounds of their Tenants, <hi>coniurati;</hi> ſworne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> Though Chriſt ſaid,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.16</note> 
               <hi>Baptize all nations;</hi> Though <hi>Paul baptized whole houſholds;</hi> though<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2.39.</note> 
               <hi>Promiſes,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 10.47.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>kingdome,</hi> belongs to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, yet, after Anabaptiſts, neuer meant Chriſt to admit Infants to his baptiſme? for as eaſie had it beene for him to name them, had hee ſo inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as to leaue it determinable, by doubtfull conſequetiall deductions. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 3. Their third ground they haue borrowed, vnwittingly it may be, from the ſchoole of <hi>Thomas;</hi> the beſt Patron, I dare ſay, of their opinion. That the ancient practiſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> before the law written, was arbitrary onely, without any iniunction, or prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of God. And yet, ſaith, <hi>Thomas, Abraham</hi> had his Propheticall inſtinct which was to him a law. And may wee thinke their ſacrificing, and like deuotions, or pious offices, were done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniunctions? <hi>By faith Abel offered.</hi> Heb. 11. Therefore not without a word of God<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 26.13.</note>. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham kept Gods charge, his commandements, his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, his lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The names, the ſame, as of thoſe lawes after giuen in writing, force vs to thinke, they had their rule of faith, of worſhip, of life, according to which they were bound to frame their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and life. Euen of the particular, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Tything, it ſhall after appeare, it was done of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of Iuſtice, by iniunction, and therefore not, as is ſuppoſed, arbitrarily.</p>
            <p>Thus the introduction to our intendment. How loth am I, that couetouſneſſe ſhould grow impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo impious, as without warrant, or ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to abrogate any law of God, intended to bee perpetuall: how faine would I perſwade conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (and if there be any, it will be perſwaded) to prooue, before it affirme, the law of Tything abrogated; to evidence, before it pleade exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from it; They erre, that thinke vs onely bound, by reaſons to prooue ſuch lawes perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: thoſe that ſcize the Lords ancient inheritance to themſelues, thoſe that detaine any part of that portion, muſt prooue it temporary, before they can warrant conſcience in ſuch practiſe, Cleerely God gaue ſuch a law; according to it, practiſed Patriarches, Iewes, Chriſtians vpon perſwaſion of obligation; ancients, as many as treated it, iudge it to binde the Chriſtian Church. The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the reaſons of none, except demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, ſhall ſway my iudgement, nor ought to ſway anies, to thinke it temporary, belonging onely to the time, and ſtate of the Iewes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A taſte of Lay-mens reaſons, much ſwaying their conſcience, let me, though ſomething out of place, giue you; A pidling Cauiller, willing to ſhew his witte, would needes frame argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tything, of the text, which gaue mee firſt occaſion to treate the queſtion. After many quarrellings againſt choice of that text of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. to ſupport the concluſion, thus hee <hi>quaerees.</hi> What if from this text hee could frame an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Tythes? <hi>Anſ.</hi> He ſhould bee to me <hi>Magnus Apollo.</hi> And if out of this, or any other holy text, you could handſomely but <hi>ſtraine</hi> an argument, I would yeeld you the concluſion.</p>
            <p>Its well with you, my Lay-maſters, you haue in our free hold the eleuen points of the law. I dare ſay, you ſhall ſooner fetch water out of a flint, then argument out of Scripture, to prooue your <hi>ius</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>Yet this Text would afford ſome <hi>Sampſon</hi> one. What, trow we, may that be? if hyre or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bee the maintenance belonging to miniſters, then not Tythes: for hire is a ciuill thing, and from men by ciuill contract. Tythes are challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from God, as a diuine donation. Therefore Tythes, and wages, being of diuers nature, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not both be the miniſters maintenance. But the maintenance, belonging to miniſters, is hyre or wages. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Ergo:</hi> not Tythes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wittie too too: <hi>quaſi dicam,</hi> if an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be the maintenance belonging to <hi>Leui,</hi> then
<pb facs="tcp:133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> not Tythes: for inheritances are ciuill things, deſcending lineally from father to ſon, ſetled vpon poſterity, by ciuill, or naturall, or nationall law. Tythes are challenged to <hi>Leui</hi> from God, as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine donation; but the maintenance belonging to <hi>Leui,</hi> is an inheritance. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Ergo,</hi> not Tythes. How eaſie is it to anſwer, that Tythes was that inheritance, and Tythes is this wages? Will you reſt in an anſwer when you haue it? The Apoſtle ſaith not, our maintenance, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is, is wages, or hyre giuen by ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. But from proportion of wages giuen in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to ſouldiors, &amp;c. proues a reward or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, due to Miniſters for preaching the Goſpel. 2. Is euery hire or wages due by ciuill contract? The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or wages of ſinne is death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. by ciuill contract thinke you? betwixt whom, and the ſinner. 3. Alters this the nature of things, to haue many efficients? Laſtly, if hyre, then not Tythes? what if Tythes be this hyre? as it was <hi>Leuies</hi> inheritance. Then though hyre, yet Tythes. Hyre imports the generall, Tythes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the particular: hath not this <hi>Sampſon</hi> puld the houſe vpon our heads.</p>
            <p>A ſecond argument thence drawne, is from <hi>Pauls</hi> ſilencing of the particular, where hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely treates of the generall. <hi>Paul</hi> purpoſely treating of Miniſters maintenance for perpetuitie, mentions not Tythes, where one word yet had ſtrooke the matter dead.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Will it pleaſe you to know, that <hi>Pauls</hi> principall ſcope is not, to treate of maintenance; but to perſwade the people, to yeeld of right in things indifferent, in fauour of the weake, by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawne from his example. Hee yieldes in maintenance, therefore ought they in matters of leſſe moment. His ſecondary intention is, to auow his right to maintenance: where, though grounds be laid that concerne poſteritie, yet is not that his maine purpoſe.</p>
            <p>His concluſion in this ſecond intention is, that he and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had right to maintenance: muſt he needes deſcend to expreſſe mention of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>quantum?</hi> eſpecially it beeing elſe-where ſufficiently determined? what if he thought the people well enough able, out of the old Scriptures to informe themſelues of the particular? This once is apparent. Scriptures of new Teſtament deale leſt particularly, in matters plainely, and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly particularized in the old; as in thoſe maine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, of obſeruing Sabbath, and forbearing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, &amp;c. is euident.</p>
            <p>But to this Argument, <hi>Paul</hi> purpoſing to ſpeake of miniſters maintenance, mentions not Tythes. <hi>Ergo</hi> what? they are not due? or no thought in <hi>Paul</hi> of Tythes, as if I ſhould ſay:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> purpoſing to ſet forth the<note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> 
               <hi>history of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> mentions not Angels: are they therefore not created? or had <hi>Moſes</hi> no thought of their creation?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Our Sauiour purpoſely treating of the<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law,</hi> and continuance thereof, ſpeaketh not particularly of the Sabbath. How much quaeſtion hath the Church beene peſtered withall about that Subiect? Sure our Sauiour much forgot himſelfe, eſpecially hauing praeſcience of things to come, that he gaue not one touch at moralitie of Sabbath, where one word had ſtroke the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dead. Are ye ſatisfied? ſuch arguments are the beſt, that theſe mens Logicke can frame;</p>
            <p>Proceede we now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to reuiew of the quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; ſtating it after our old courſe, for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillers ſake, who hath laboured to perplexe it; Who knowes whether God will more bleſſe our ſecond indeauours?</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:133:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133:9"/>
            <head>THE MINISTERS PORTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE grants on all ſides are theſe. Firſt, that there is a maintenance<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.4, 5. to 15.</note> 
               <hi>in iustice due</hi> to Miniſters for their worke ſake. Secondly, Its yeelded it muſt be <hi>competent,</hi> not only for ſupply of naturall neceſſities, but for their<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>furniture</hi> to <hi>euery good worke</hi> of their calling. Thirdly, That it muſt be<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>liberall:</hi> not ſuch as euery niggardly minde will iudge conuenient and competent.</p>
            <p>To which grants, let me adde theſe <hi>poſtulata,</hi> as plainly determined in Scripture. Let no man miſtake the terme, ſuppoſing them to be Lawyers <hi>quaerees,</hi> or matters of <hi>moot.</hi> My <hi>postulata</hi> are Mathematica, ſuch as to my apprehenſion, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of euidence and certenty, admit none, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept cauilſome, contradiction. Thoſe granted,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133:10"/> ſome inferences for the maine purpoſe, will, of their owne accord, follow. Thus you may num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That to Miniſters of the Goſpel, belongs a maintenance as large, as to the Leuiticall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: this, mee thinkes,<note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> 
               <hi>excellencie of</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, and<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>bleſsings</hi> conferred thereby enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Yet Christ whoſe Miniſterie, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings were ſuperiour to ours, thought not neceſſarie His excellencie ſhould bee adorned with earthly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now you are in the right. Neither thought he neceſſary, that th'excellencie of his Kingdome ſhould be adorned with Royall mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence. What is your inference? therefore our<note n="f" place="margin">Math. 6.29.</note> 
               <hi>Salomons may not bee clothed royaltie?</hi> therefore nor his Miniſters<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>haue where to lay their heads?</hi> Know you not that his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on earth, was to be carried in the<note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>habitude of a ſeruant?</hi> and that<note n="i" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>by his pouertie he ſhould make vs rich?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That this maintenance muſt riſe<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>out of all and</hi> euery <hi>the goods of all and euery the people instructed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Lord hath as certainly prouided for our maintenance vnder the Goſpel, as for theirs vnder the Law. For had the Lord leſſe care of vs? was there leſſe need in reſpect of the peoples backwardneſſe? no. But hee entruſted Magiſtrates with that care.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And were there not Magiſtrates amongſt the Iewes.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Is not the care of God ſhowne ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ordaining maintenance without certeintie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thats not the <hi>quaere,</hi> whither ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but whither leſſe or more by determining certeintie, or by leauing all to mans arbitrement. As if I ſhould aske; doth not the father, aſſigning his childe to the care of friends at large, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prouide for his liuelihood; as allotting his ſonne a portion of lands and reuenue, which none may by any meanes defeat him of? I ſhould thinke his care more, that thus certeinly prouides, then his, who commits all to the doubtfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of friends.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>But why thinkes M. Selater, the people vnder the Goſpel, as backward as thoſe vnder the Law? When God hath promiſed</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ioel 2.28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>more abundant Grace: Is not Iustice a part of Grace? can Grace be without Iuſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Grace renewing cannot be without Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: vertues gratious are connexed. But the Grace of which <hi>Ioel</hi> ſpeakes, dreaming dreames, and ſeeing viſions, or if there be any other, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnder the terme of <hi>Gratia gratis data,</hi> may bee without Iuſtice: except perhaps wee may thinke <hi>Iudas</hi> iuſt, becauſe to him was giuen, as to others,<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>power to doe miracles.</hi> Howbeit it muſt be confeſſed, that Grace of illumination, and ſanctification, is greater vnder the Goſpel, then vnder the Law: 1. In extent of the ſubiects
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133:11"/> receiuing; which are now all fleſh, as well Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, as Iewes. 2. <hi>Menſura &amp; gradu,</hi> where it takes place, making the termes of compariſon aequall. But thinke you, this Grace takes place in all vnder the new Teſtament? or meant the Lord to leaue vs to the gratious diſpoſition of our ſanctified people onely, exempting others from bond of dutie, in contributing to mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the miniſterie? I aſſure you Sir, if I ſhould meaſure mens Sanctification by their Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in this kinde, I ſhould be forced to aſſigne Sanctification ratheſt to men of leſt knowledge; and to ſay of others, who haue encloſed ſanctitie, and ſinceritie all to themſelues, <hi>Non eſt qui facit iuſtum vſque ad vnum.</hi> Whither it be, that the holy morſell is ſweet; or that they would haue iuſtice in this kinde, ſeeme mercie; or how the good yeare it falles, I know not; <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquit:</hi> This Iuſtice is taken to her wings, and fled farre from our coaſtes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Lord in the Leuiticall Law had eye to prouiſion for vs, that were to Miniſter in the Goſpel.<note n="n" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not muſſell the mouth of the oxe which treadeth out the corne,</hi> was a branch of Law Leuiticall; yet applyed by th'Apoſtle to enforce honourable maintenance of Miniſters vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Thus farre I thinke we walke ſafely, ſith in the very ſteps of the holy Ghoſt, leading vs in the new Teſtament: Let vs now deſcend toward the particular.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:133:11"/>
            <p>Some tumbling downe headlong, rather then deſcending, reſolue of a competencie indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; ſo th'allowance be competent all is well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Then in caſe of this fancied competencie, ſome as the inſtructed, though wealthy perhaps, ſhall be exempted from the Apoſtles iniunction. For ſuppoſe ſome one or two of the well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hearers, ſhall out of their priuate, make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent allowance; The reſt ſhall now<note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor 9 12.</note> 
               <hi>reape our ſpirituals, and not ſow their carnals.</hi> For, as the ſaying is riſe enough in a Miniſters maintenance, enough is a feaſt. But ſaith th' Apoſtle,<note n="p" place="margin">Gal 6.6</note> 
               <hi>Let him,</hi> that is: euery him, <hi>that is inſtructed, make his inſtructer partaker of all his goods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſuppoſed (ſaith the Cauiller) is without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, nigh to an impoſsibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. It ſhould ſeeme then, the Grace of the new Testament is not euery where alike aboundant, and ouerflowing.</hi> In your countries it workes more ſparely. My ſelfe haue knowne many, who, out of their owne priuate, haue giuen, ouer and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue their Tythes ordinary to the Ignorant or idle Sheepheard, a largeſſe, as large as moſt men thinke competent, in zeale of their owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what inconuenience, though contribution ariſe not out of all and euery able mans goods?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.11</note> 
               <hi>They reape our ſpirituals</hi> without <hi>ſowing their Carnalls.</hi> 2. They diſcharge not the<note n="r" place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> duties laide on them <hi>by the Apoſtle,</hi> and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle their conſcience with guilt of ſinne. An
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133:12"/> inconuenience call you that,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> or a miſchiefe? Not ſo, <hi>for that of Paul is but a counſell, not a praecept.</hi> 2. <hi>A counſell to be obeyed in caſu of the Miniſters neede. Then indeede the hearers are bound, to affoord their Minister, a meales meat, or nights lodging, and ſuch like cleemoſynarie kindneſſe, as they would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord another man in his neceſsitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When will you ceaſe to peruert the ſtreight waies of the Lord? Are Miniſters your Almes-men? Is nothing due to them <hi>ex lege Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae</hi> for their labour in the word and doctrine, be they neuer ſo well ſtored of their owne, but only in mercie, reſpecting their neceſſities? Is this the<note n="s" place="margin">1. Tim 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>double honour Paul</hi> would haue them <hi>thought worthy of?</hi> This<note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>th'ordinance of Chriſt, for Preachers of the Goſpel, to liue of the Goſpel?</hi> what if our inheritances ciuill were as large, as yours? Is nothing due for our paines in the Goſpel? how then liue we of the Goſpel? what is the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers deſerued hyre? the ſouldiers <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In caſe of need, you that haue this worlds good, will not ſee this Brother want.</hi> There, there ſo would you haue it Miniſters, to hang on your beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; to partake workes of your mercie due to humanitie; but neither by this, nor any other text of Scripture, to be intituled to any thing for their worke ſake.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> This and no more muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this <hi>praecept</hi> of th'Apoſtle. <hi>For the charge is as great in the next verſe, to releeue the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> But thinke you that alſo a counſell, not a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133:12"/> praecept. 2. Weigh well, you ſhall be forced to ſee, that what is ſaid in the three next verſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the point in hand of Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; not to beneuolence towards the poore. Let me ſee what this mercifull man hath ſaid hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto for the qualitie of our maintenance. One while its hire, as much, or little as you can make your bargaine for; Another while, Almes: your ſeruants, or your beades-men we are, one of the two certaine. Sir, I would you knew, the only Maſter we ſerue is Ieſus Chriſt: His ſeruants we are. Our peoples<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 13.7.17. 1. Theſſ. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>guides, rulers, ſuperiours.</hi> And the maintenance wee claime, is of that portion, which the God of heauen hath aſſigned vs; which who without Sacriledge can detaine from vs? But proceede we in examining the likelihood of your competencie. See concluſion the ſixt: and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighing it, tell me, whither thou finde conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſatisfied with this imaginarie competencie? for is there no certaine prouiſion for Miniſters of the Goſpel, but this vncertaine competency? who ſhall iudge of it? Euery man? <hi>Mallem Cerberum metueres,</hi> as the Orator ſpeakes. The Magiſtrate? why would not the Lord leaue this to Iewiſh Magiſtrates? no not to <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man ſo gratious with him? and leaue it to Magiſtrates vnder the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obiect."/> 
               <hi>Iewiſh Magiſtrates were then intruſted.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sol."/> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What? as you would haue them now Truſters for vs; that the whole of our maintenance ſhould depend vpon their diſcretion, to aſſigne, leſſe or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133:13"/> more? Where haue you it? in what Scripture? in what Authentique Authour? will the <hi>text in</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Malachi</hi> beare it? Let the reader be iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obiect."/>
               <hi>No ſuch certentie was left to Leuites, as we now claime. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sol."/> Anſ.</hi> No ſuch certeinty. <hi>Ergo</hi> none? 2. Such certeintie: ſo ſuch as its the ſame for the generall. Tythes, and Glebe, and votarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations. 3. Why none ſuch? <hi>Ob. Tythes were then brought to one common Store-houſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhare giuen to euery one, according to his gifts, worth, number of children, and neceſsity.</hi> Anſ. 1. <hi>Incerta omnia;</hi> whether worth, or neceſſitie, or ſpecialtie of imployment, were the rule of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution: whether all Tythes were brought to one common ſtore-houſe at Ieruſalem; or not rather laide vp in the ſeuerall Cities, aſſigned to Leuites in the ſeuerall Tribes. 2. Varies it the ſuchnes or identitie of the matter of maintenance, that there were ſome variable circumſtances ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to the payment or diſtribution? 3. Thus conceiue your anſwer. The whole of Tythes was a certaintie due to the comminaltie of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites: The whole of Tythes is a certentie due to the comminaltie of Miniſters. A portion of that whole, was due to euery Leuite. A portion of this whole, due to euery Miniſter of the Goſpel. 1. <hi>Res diſtributa</hi> was then certaine, Tythes. 2. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectum distributionis,</hi> certaine: Leuites, not Laickes. 3. <hi>Modus distributionis,</hi> in reſpect of the particular, in a ſort indeterminate, while the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was for Leuites to liue in common: Our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133:13"/> 
               <hi>res diſtribuenda,</hi> is certaine: the perſons, to whom that portion muſt be diſtributed, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. The <hi>Modus diſtributionis,</hi> in a ſort vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; as what number of people, or circuit of place to be aſſigned to particular miniſters; what miniſters to bee deputed to ouerſight of this, or that congregation; yet <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> certaine; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch congregations aſſigned, to ſuch mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Tythes thence accrewing belong to thoſe miniſters by <hi>Pauls</hi> rule. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe it committed to Magiſtrates? how I demand; abſolutely, or with limitation? if with limits, what are thoſe bounds? forſooth a Competencie. Perceiue you not circling and meere vncertainties? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obiect."/> 
               <hi>The Magistrate is bounded with no certentie of number or quantitie? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sol."/> Anſw.</hi> What? <hi>Ergo,</hi> with no limits at all; which is the quaeſtion. <hi>Obiect. Yes, a rule he hath to follow,</hi> the <hi>word of God. Anſw.</hi> That is large. But what is the rule, or limit preſcribed for this particular by the word of God? Say if you can without circ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Forſooth Competencie. You are coniured to your circle, and muſt not out of it.</p>
            <p>Leaue we therfore this fancy: and ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may finde ſome other more certaine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to reſolue of. And ſurely, when we haue in vaine turmoiled our ſelues to auoide Iudaizing in this point of Miniſters maintenance, we ſhall be forced at length to acknowledge Tenthes, which ſome call Iewiſh, to bee the Miniſters appointed Portion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:133:14"/>
            <p>That the truth may better appeare, I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the different opinions that I haue met withall in this point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Browniſts in this quaeſtion thus peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolue. That Tythes are ſo meerely caeremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; Leuitical, that they cannot without betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Euangelicall libertie, and diſauowing Chriſts Prieſthood, bee retayned as maintenance of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell. And how full ſoeuer of dotage, this dreame may ſeeme; yet this I will ſay for them; they are mad with more reaſon a great deale, then any others which holde them caeremonies Leuiticall. If the aſſumption were true, their concluſion would ſoundly follow by doctrine of th' Apoſtle. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. &amp; 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some others thinking them Iudicials, reſolue: part, that they may be retained as the Miniſters ſtipend: part, that they are the moſt conuenient maintenance can be allotted vs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ſort, that they are due by Gods Law to Miniſters of the Goſpel: but theſe in explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themſelues diuerſly deriue them thence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some thus, due by Gods law enioyning obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Magiſtrates in things lawfull and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. Theſe giue them no other ground in Gods word, then other humane ordinances.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others, due by Gods Law, in as much as the Church (whoſe authoritie with them is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine) hath enioyned their payment. So generally Papiſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third ſort: due by Gods Law; in reſpect
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133:14"/> of their conſecration to God, eyther by receiued cuſtome or conſent of Churches, or by donation of Princes, or by legacie of Teſtators. In which opinion I muſt needes profeſſe my ſelfe to haue ſometime beene; till being to deliuer my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my people, I more purpoſely ſet my ſelfe to ſee what the truth was. And during that miſtake, I thus thought: that they could not without Sacriledge be aliened from their general end. My reaſons were theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I found <hi>Salomon</hi> auerring it to be <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Pro. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe to deuoure holy things,</hi> and had ſeene the curſe exemplified on many.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ordinance of the Lord I held morall and perpetuall.<note n="x" place="margin">Leuit. 27.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing ſeparate from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe, no not of thoſe which man had ſeparated, might be againe vnhallowed, no nor redeemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſaying of th' Apoſtle much ſwayed with me<note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>If it be but a mans Testament, no man abrogates it.</hi> 1. No man ought to abrogate it. And ſo much the more, for that being once an Auditour of that Iudicious Diuine Maſter <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> whoſe memory is bleſſed, I heard him mooue the doubt; whether things giuen to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious vſes, ſuppoſe to maintaine Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monging, might be alienated. And thus aſſoile to my remembrance. That from the particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, wherein through ignorance they erred, alienation might be; But from the generall end, maintenance of Gods worſhip, they might not be aliened. Thus then and vpon thoſe grounds,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133:15"/> my iudgement is ſtill the ſame, though my <hi>Media</hi> be other, and ſomewhat more peremptorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is not Maſter</hi> Sclaters <hi>concluſion to take away Tythes, is Sacrilege? Be not his other Media ſince his miſtake reformed, becauſe Tythes bee due</hi> iure diuino; <hi>abſolutely and</hi> ſimpliciter, <hi>and not</hi> quodam modo, <hi>as by conſecration; why then makes Master</hi> Sclaters <hi>conſecration one of his fiue reaſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Maſter <hi>Sclaters</hi> opinion is that Tythes are due <hi>iure diuino;</hi> that is, by principles, and Lawes of the word of God, abſolutely due; by ſuch abſolute preſcript as admits no repeale or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why then returnes he to the matter of conſecration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe that is one of his grounds of clayme, laide downe in the word of God; which once was his onely, is now one amongſt others. 2. Withall you muſt vnderſtand, there is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſecration; one by <hi>Gods reſeruing, or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating things to himſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 27.</note> Another, <hi>by humane vow, or dedication.</hi> Maſter <hi>Sclaters</hi> miſtake was, that they were due onely by humane conſecration: his reformed iudgement is, that they are holy to God, not onely becauſe vowed by men, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe reſerued to God by himſelfe from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Here is no tantologie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect. Alienation was made by the whole ſtate, which hath intereſt in</hi> meum <hi>and</hi> tuum.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Varies it the Nature of the action, ſuppoſing it to be Sacrilegious, that whole ſtates are engaged therein? Belike the multitude of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133:15"/> offendours, <hi>parit errori patrocinium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Yeeld States to haue intereſt in <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum;</hi> haue they dominion ouer that which is <hi>Dei? Suum cuique,</hi> is a good rule for ſtates. Let them giue to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſars:</hi> to euery one, what is his owne; onely let Gods portion be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and kept inuiolable: let his dominion and property be holden a tranſcendent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Quaeſt."/> 
               <hi>But what if theſe diſperſions into many hands was th'onely meanes to baniſh Antichrist?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Thoſe many hands might haue been as well Clericke as Layicke, and that end as well atchieued. 2. But<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>may you doe euill, that good may come of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Returne of Antichrist was feared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> O worthy wight, and worſhipt might he be; who neuer ſpared woman in his luſt, nor man in his rage, yet feared the returne of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. <hi>Credam?</hi> 2. But know you not Ignorance the greateſt pillar of Antichriſts Kingdome? If amongſt any he may recouer his old poſſeſſion by a <hi>Postliminium,</hi> moſt amongſt thoſe congregations which are moſt ſtript of Tythes; forced, poore ſoules, to content themſelues with Prieſts of the loweſt of the people, becauſe the ancient ſalary is ſeized on, and poſſeſſed in Lay-fee.<note place="margin">Neh 13.10, 11, 12.</note> And ſee iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues of ſuch dealing, with meanes of reformation.</p>
            <p>Quaeſt. <hi>But can any in errour conſecrate vnto God? was Cains ſacrifice accepted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What is your meaning? ſo as <hi>their act,</hi> as theirs, <hi>ſhall pleaſe God?</hi> and their perſons bee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133:16"/> accepted, ſo we anſwer; no. And ſo much onely preſſeth your inſtance in <hi>Cain.</hi> But ſo as <hi>to giue God propertie in the thing conſecrated,</hi> who doubts but they may? The Cenſers of <hi>Corah</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> muſt be employed about the Altar; becauſe, though erroneouſly, yet<note n="a" place="margin">Num. 16.38</note> 
               <hi>they offered them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord: therefore they are hallowed.</hi> And for this I am ſure, you haue Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> firme in his poſt-humous Notes. Things conſecrated er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneouſly,<note place="margin">ad Galat 3.</note> may bee imployed to the vſe of Gods worſhip: yea the next heire of the Votarie, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all title to things ſo conſecrated: and may not claime them from their generall intendment: though to him, if to any, they belong of right, in caſe there bee a nullitie of erroneous conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Price of a whore muſt not bee brought into the Tabernacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, hire taken for her proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to filthines: of <hi>turpe lucrum,</hi> God will haue no ſacrifice. <hi>Ergo,</hi> not of goods honeſtly gotten by the votarie? 2. Beſides, know you not that the caſe is ruled? that euen of vniuſt perquiſites, ſomething may redound to poore, ſomething to Church, where the parties ſuffering wrong, are not; or are vnknowne; 3. But is your Whore, the Whore of Babylon? Methinkes I ſmell you; I doubt our <hi>Albe,</hi> wherein wee miniſter, will heare no better from you, then the Whores ſmocke, though in vſe long time before, Antichriſt transferred it to his ſuperſtition.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:133:16"/>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>This were to ſit in th' Idols Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Vnderſtand you what you ſay? To retaine the conſecrations of Idolaters to Gods ſeruice, how is it more to grace an Idol, then to keepe vp Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wherein Idols haue beene worſhipped, and apply them to the worſhip of God? S. <hi>Paul</hi> could diſtinguiſh, betwixt <hi>eating an Idolothyte, and eating it</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 8.7</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. It may ſuffice, that they bee diuerted to the worſhip of the true God, whether they were, in the generall ayme of the Donors, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,</p>
            <p>But <hi>quorſum haec tam multa?</hi> Its yeelded you <hi>ex abundante</hi> in explication of the fourth Argument, that ſuch erroneous conſecrations giue not God ſeizure in things deuoted. A new and holy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration without errour we haue of Tythes, and ſuch like holy things; beſide their ancient reſeruation from the beginning, with that proteſtation of the Lord.<note n="c" place="margin">Leu. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Tythes are holy vnto the Lord:</hi> what this Mome hath gayned by his quarrelling hitherto, the learned eaſily iudge. Proceede we therefore to our concluſion, which is thus propounded and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed.</p>
            <p>Tythes are the portion, at leaſt, part of that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by Gods word allotted to Miniſters for their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>By Tythes vnderſtand the tenth part of all the hearers increaſe: that is; to ſtoppe the mouth of the Cauiller, of his<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>income</hi> or <hi>reuenue.</hi> Particulars may be read. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 27.30. <hi>Et alibi:</hi> In a word, to vſe the diſtinction of Canoniſts; whether they bee perſonall, of meere induſtry, negotiation, &amp;c. or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133:17"/> praediall, as of grounds, &amp;c. or mixt, as of Cattell, the tenthes of the whole income, not thoſe of <hi>Cummin &amp; Annyſe</hi> excepted, fall within compaſſe of our ſubiect.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Part of the Portion: here is vncerteintie ſtill,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Cauiller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> None at all. That part is our certeine Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: other we haue; if you would know what: It is, whatſoeuer the regular deuotion of Princes, or people, ſhall pleaſe to adde as, an auctarie to our maintenance. <hi>Zepperus de lege Moſaica. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 40. <hi>Decimae, pars ſunt illius ſtipendij, quod ministris pro officj ſui laboribus, diuino &amp; naturali iure debentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> By Gods word allotted. <hi>Intends Master</hi> Sclater <hi>without any ground of ciuill or eccleſiasticall ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Maſter <hi>Sclater</hi> meanes: though no ordinance of man ſhould aſſigne them vnto vs. <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſsimum Dei verbum,</hi> hath made them ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In what Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As they are an honouring of God, ſo in the firſt: As they tend to preſerue the publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, ſo in the ſecond and fourth: As main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of our perſons, ſo in the fift, being part of the honour due to the ſpirituall parent.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>But without any point of Conſecration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though no conſecration votarie had bin from man, yet were they ours by the word of God. Howbeit the lawes for ſuch conſecrations giuen in the word of God, hitherto belong, and fall within our whole of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Of Tithes amongſt Iewes we finde foure ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tithes of Leuites. 2. of Prieſts? 3. for loue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133:17"/> Feaſts: 4. and Tythes for the poore: heare vs in <hi>Hieromes</hi> termes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hoc est, decimam partem omnium frugum Leuiticae tribui populus ex lege debebat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Rurſum ex ipſis decimis, Leuitae, hoc eſt inferior miniſtrorum gradus, decimas dabat ſacerdotibus; &amp; haec eſt quae appellatur</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Erant quoque &amp; aliae decimae, quas vnuſquiſque de populo. Iſrael in ſuis horreis ſeparabat, vt comede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret eas cum iret in Templum in vrbe Hieruſalem, &amp; in veſtibulo Templi: &amp; ſacerdotes ac Leuitas inuitarent ad conuiuia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Erant autem &amp; aliae decimae, quas pauperibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condebant; quae Graeco ſermone appellantur.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hieronym: in Ezech. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>ad cap.</hi> 45.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> though he mention three kinds onely, becauſe he compriſes the <hi>ſecundance</hi> in Tythes of Leuites, (perhaps hauing eye to thoſe only payable from the people,) yet in effect acknowledgeth the <hi>quadripartite</hi> diſtinction; at leaſt diſchargeth not the people of their <hi>trietericall;</hi> thus preſenting vs the Law from the mouth of the Law-giuer. <hi>Vltra duas decimas quas quotannis pendere iam iuſsi,</hi> 1. <hi>Alteram Leuitis,</hi> 2. <hi>Alteram in ſacras epulas,</hi> 3. <hi>Tertia tertio quoque anno est conferenda, quae in egenas viduas &amp; pupillos diſtribuatur. Antiquitat. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Whether payment of feſtiuall Tythes were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the third yeare, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Selden</hi> would from the <hi>Septuagints</hi> rendring inferre, is a quaeſtion to our maine impertinent. Howbeit to mee it ſeemes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable; for were they in that yeare freed from <hi>their appearing at Hieruſalem? or might they in that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> yeare appeare emptie handed before the Lord?</hi> A <hi>Iustiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> perhaps there might be in that reſpect for that Time. To the <hi>Septuagint</hi> I giue the honour due to them; but dare not preferre them to the text, as now extant with points; eſpecially where the reading of th'originall is ſo conſtant and vnuaried. Beſides who knowes not their manifold aberrations in matters of no ſmall moment? as in that of the Chronologie in Geneſis, wherein ſo many haue in vaine laboured a reconcilement. The obſeruation out of their ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring muſt be confeſſed to be acute: yet hath in it rather wittie diligence of obſeruation, then ſoliditie to build inference.</p>
            <p>If any make quaeſtion of whether ſort we diſpute; Tythes we meane of that Nature with thoſe paide to Leuites; which, perhaps, are therefore conuey'd to them in the terme of an<note n="e" place="margin">Num. 18.</note> 
               <hi>inheritance,</hi> becauſe the Lawgiuer would imply their perpetuitie, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall deſcent from Miniſtery to Miniſterie vnto all generations. The why nots raiſed about other kindes, will beſt be anſwered in diſcuſſing th'obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>Of theſe Tythes this is that we affirme. That by the word of God they belong for euer to Miniſters of holy things; and therefore in theſe dayes to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, who alone haue now to doe with publique miniſtrations of the worſhip of God. Our reaſons are theſe. The firſt grounded on <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.6.8. <hi>He whoſe deſcent is not counted from them, receiued Tythes of Abraham:</hi> and verſ. 8. <hi>Here men that die, receiue Tythes: but there he receiueth them, of whom its witneſſed, that he liueth.</hi> Compare, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:133:18"/>
            <p>The Argument which this Scripture affoords, hath receiued much diſaduantage, by ſlender colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many, thus onely preſſing it. Tythes were paide to Prieſts before the Leuiticall law was giuen. Therefore their payment is founded rather on Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall then Caeremoniall law. To which, anſwer is well giuen; that by as good inference, ſacrificing of beaſts may be prooued a moralitie, ſith it was alſo in vſe before giuing of the Law by <hi>Moſes.</hi> That we may the better ſee the force of the Argument, let vs a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſider the frame and ſumme of the text. The Apoſtle by occaſion of the peoples dulneſſe, hauing digreſſed from <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.11. to <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.20. returnes to his purpoſe; that is, to ſhew the excellencie of Chriſts Prieſthood aboue that of <hi>Aaron,</hi> by auouching him a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec.</hi> The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is this. Chriſts Prieſthood is more excellent then that of Leui; or Chriſt is a greater Prieſt then any after <hi>Aarons</hi> order. The principall reaſon lyeth thus. He that is a Prieſt after th'order of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is a greater Prieſt then the Prieſts after <hi>Aaron.</hi> But Chriſt is a Prieſt after th'order of <hi>Melchiſedec. Ergo:</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>minor</hi> hath firſt his proofe. 1. From a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Dauid, Cap.</hi> 5.20. 2. From that abſolute agreement betwixt <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> and Chriſt: the parts whereof are theſe. 1. As <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was King, and Prieſt of the moſt high God, ſo Chriſt. 2. As <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> King of righteouſneſſe, and Prince of peace, ſo Chriſt. 3. As <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his parents, kinred, beginning and end of life are not recorded; ſo Chriſt, as man, without father, as God without mother, kinred, beginning, and end of life. Therefore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133:19"/> Chriſt is truly a Prieſt after th'order of <hi>Melchiſedec: verſe</hi> 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> remaines to be prooued, and that hath proofe from <hi>verſe</hi> 4. to 11. the ſumme whereof is compriſed in this principall Syllogiſme. If <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec</hi> be greater then <hi>Leui,</hi> then he that is a Prieſt after his order, as Chriſt is; is greater then <hi>Leui.</hi> But <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec</hi> is greater then <hi>Leui, Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Minor</hi> proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: Greater then <hi>Abraham,</hi> greater then <hi>Leui: Melchiſedec</hi> is greater then <hi>Abraham: Ergo</hi> then <hi>Leui: Minor</hi> prooued. Hee to whom <hi>Abraham</hi> paide Tythes, of whom he was bleſſed, is greater then <hi>Abraham.</hi> But to <hi>Melchiſedec, Abraham</hi> paide Tythes; and <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham. Ergo,</hi> is greater then he. <hi>verſe</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Argument proouing the greatneſſe of this Prieſt, aboue thoſe of <hi>Aarons</hi> order, is laide downe <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. A tyth-taker, that is, a Prieſt of whom its teſtified that he liues, is greater then a Tyth-taker that dies. But the Prieſt after <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is a Tyth-taker of whom its teſtified that he liues. Leuites take Tythes and die. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Prieſt after <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his order is greater then the Prieſts Leuiticall. This is in my ſimple Logicke the diſpoſition of the text. As for illuſtrations, or amplifications by proſyllogiſmes prolepſes, or otherwiſe, I purpoſely omit them. Now me thinkes, the text thus naturally reſolued, there ſhould need no farther deduction of th'Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yet that the ſimpleſt may ſee what footing Tythes haue here, thus I collect it.</p>
            <p>The portion due to Chriſts Prieſthood, is due to Miniſters of the Goſpel; Tythes are the portion due to Chriſts Prieſthood. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:133:19"/>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is thus proued. The portion due to <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec</hi> his Prieſthood, is due to Chriſts Prieſthood. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. for that Chriſt is Prieſt after that order. 2. other things enunciated of <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> are true of Chriſt eminently &amp; alwaies: as its eminently &amp; alwaies true of Chriſt, that he is King of righteouſnes &amp; Prince of peace: eminently and alwaies true of Chriſt, he is without pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, without beginning &amp; end of life, that he bleſſeth <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; all his ſeed, &amp;c. All theſe are more properly verified of Chriſt, then of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his Type. Why not then alſo this euer true of him? <hi>He taketh Tythes.</hi> May we not aſſume? Tythes are the portion due to <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his Prieſthood? 1. Paide they were by <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> as due to his Prieſthood. 2. In the Apoſtles Logique a Prieſt, and a receiuer of Tythes are aequipollents. In ſteed of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, men that die <hi>are Prieſts,</hi> he ſaith, men that die <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Tythes:</hi> In ſteed of ſaying, he that liues is <hi>a Prieſt,</hi> he ſaith, he that liues, <hi>takes tythes:</hi> as if, in his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Tythes and Prieſthood were as inſeparable, as king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and tribute: The <hi>Maior</hi> of the principall Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme if any doubt of, to wit, whether the portion due to Chriſt, be due to Miniſters, let him compare, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. where is th'expreſſe ordinance of Chriſt, <hi>that Ministers ſhould liue of the Goſpel.</hi> 2. Who in likelihood ſhould be his receiuers, but thoſe that are <hi>in his ſtead,</hi> as is ſaid of Miniſters, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. 3. The ſame reaſon which the Lord aſſignes of <hi>Leui</hi> his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in things to himſelfe reſerued, and ſanctified, is true of Miniſters, or elſe of none. God is Leuites portion. 1. Gods portion is Leuites portion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were taken to Miniſter before him. Why not then alſo Chriſts portion Miniſters portion?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe they onely are aſſumed to Chriſt, to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Goſpel. A reaſon for not Tything of ſo plaine deduction out of Scripture, if any can bring mee, he ſhall much ſway mee to his ſentence.</p>
            <p>This Argument I remember once to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſomething otherwiſe, to this purpoſe. The portion due to the Prieſthood after <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his order, is due to Miniſters of the Goſpel. But Tythes are that portion. <hi>Ergo,</hi> And thus propounding it, I receiued theſe anſwers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> The propoſition ſeemes vntrue, except you can prooue your ſelues Prieſts after that order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whereto I then anſwered, that though we be no Prieſts after that order, yet is there truth in the propoſition, ſith Chriſt the high Prieſt of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to whom originally they belong, hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained vs to liue of his portion.</p>
            <p>A ſecond anſwer was by limitation: the portion due [by Law] to that Prieſthood, is due to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. But with that limitation th'aſſumption is falſe: <hi>Abrahams</hi> payment being an act rather voluntarie, then by any iniunction from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But that that act of <hi>Abraham</hi> was no act: in this ſenſe voluntarie, but rather of neceſſarie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned dutie, is euident (me thinkes) by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 1. For that gifts voluntarie, proceeding from bountie and liberalitie, imply a ſuperioritie or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie in the giuer, aboue the receiuer. For<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 20.35.</note> 
               <hi>its a more bleſſed thing in</hi> that kinde <hi>to giue then to receiue.</hi> But <hi>Abrahams</hi> payment of Tythes was teſtimonie of his inferiority. 2. Againe, the phraſe it ſelfe implies as much. <hi>Melchiſedec Tythed Abraham;</hi> ver. 6. a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133:20"/> phraſe that looſeth all his Emphaſis, if no iniunction had ſubiected <hi>Abraham</hi> to a neceſſitie of beeing tythed. 3. What meane they when they ſay of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> tything, it was done without law? would they be vnderſtood of <hi>Abrahams</hi> fact onely? or of tything at large, as it was in vſe before the Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? Now ſure I wonder how firſt <hi>Abraham,</hi> and then after him <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſhould fall vpon a tenth, rather then vpon a ſixt or twelfth part, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing preſcribed in their times for tything? 2. How prooue they but probably that it was without iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Law? if this be the reaſon, for that we finde no mention of any Law to that end giuen, by as good reaſon may they ſay of ſacrifices, and ſundry other actions religious, that they were arbitrarie; ſith we finde no expreſſe mandate giuen of them in thoſe times. But thus me thinks we may better reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their practiſe to an iniunction; theſe facts of theirs were approoued of God; therefore not done without iniunction from him. Thus farre I ſuppoſe, this Argument cleared. Volumes of new cauills are behinde; which makes mee thinke it hangs much in the teeth of oppoſites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Thus is my Cauiller. <hi>Yeeld for a while Tythes due to the Priesthood of Melchiſedec: will it thence follow they are due to Christ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſhall tell you anone, when we haue learnt your meaning. What is your meaning, by thus yeelding them due to the Prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedec?</hi> meane you the Prieſthood after that order? Then it followes that they are due to Chriſts Prieſthood: for his is <hi>Prieſthood</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>after th'order of Melchiſedec.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:133:21"/>
            <p>Perhaps that's not the meaning; but you ſuppoſe them due to <hi>Melchiſedec, ratione ſacerdotij, non talis ſacerdotij:</hi> or <hi>ratione Typica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chooſe whether you liſt. If <hi>ratione ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotij,</hi> then to Chriſt alſo; for in him is <hi>ſacerdotium.</hi> And if this bee the formall reaſon of Tythes obiect, <hi>quia</hi> and <hi>quâ ſacerdos,</hi> then they are euer due to Chriſt, becauſe that reaſon is perpetuall in him: <hi>Hee is a Priest for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>catione Typicâ,</hi> then you demand: <hi>muſt all things</hi> be <hi>verified of the truth, that of the Type, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the letter? then all that belonged to</hi> Aaron, <hi>or</hi> Sampſon, <hi>muſt be true of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> All and euery thing belonging to the Type, as a Type, muſt be verified of the Anti-type with this diſtinction, either litterally, or miſtically; not all litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, nor all myſtically: what is not litterally, muſt bee myſtically; what is not myſtically, muſt be litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. And that you may ſee ſimilitudes of heauenly things, and Earthly their Types, hold, ſome, after the letter. Reade what is ſaid of the high Prieſt of Iewes as he was Type of Chriſt.<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>He enters into the holy of holies not without bloud:</hi> As he into the holy of holies, <hi>ſo Christ into heauen:</hi> that verification is my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall. As<note n="i" place="margin">Verſ. 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>he not without bloud;</hi> So <hi>Christ not without bloud.</hi> That is literall. <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> brought in as Chriſt type in the ſtory, without father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Is not this eminently true of Chriſt after the letter? <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> without beginning or end of dayes: this alſo litterally verified. Though then all things true of the Type <hi>materialiter ſumpto,</hi> are not neceſſarily true of the <hi>Antitype;</hi> yet as many as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133:21"/> belong to the type <hi>formaliter</hi> taken, as a Type, muſt, with that diſtinction be true of th'<hi>Antitype.</hi> And what is intended to be verified myſtically, muſt ſo be verified in the truth: what is meant to be literally accompliſhed in the <hi>Antitype,</hi> muſt ſo be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>The quaeſtions then are two. 1. Whether in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Tythes <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was Type of Chriſt? 2. Whether that part of the Type be verified litterally or miſtically by th'Apoſtles doctrine?</p>
            <p>That in taking Tythes of <hi>Abraham, Melchiſedec</hi> typed out Chriſt; heare M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iunius</hi> in <hi>Gen. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Ad intelligentiam illius Typi &amp; accommodatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eius, duo maximè obſeruanda. Nempè tum in ijs quae dicuntur a Moſe, tum vero in ijs quae reticentur, conſtitui Typum. In ijs quae dicuntur; vt cum dicitur Malchitzedec, id eſt, Rex iustitiae: Rex Salem: id eſt, pacis: Sacerdos Dei Altiſsimi, benedixiſſe Abrahamo, et decimas accepiſſe. In quibus omnibus Typus Christi expreſſus obſeruandus eſt, &amp;c.</hi> What needes Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, when the Text affirmes, the Tything of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui</hi> by <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> in <hi>Abraham,</hi> prooues authentical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly th'inferioritie of Leuiticall, to Chriſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <p>That it is not myſtically, but litterally to bee fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Chriſts Prieſthood, who can denie? for where is the myſticall Analogie betwixt this Act of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> Typical, and Chriſt; as in his beeing King of <hi>Salem,</hi> and <hi>Melchiſedec;</hi> verified this muſt be of Chriſt, either litterally, or myſtically: not my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, <hi>Ergo,</hi> litterally. And ſee if the text ſay not ſo much.<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>He takes Tythes that liues euer:</hi> Who is that? <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> as the Type; Chriſt as the Truth.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133:22"/> Eminently its true of Chriſt after the letter, he liues euer; And he liues euer with this Epithete, to bee a taker of Tythes.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Nay,</hi> you ſay, <hi>The Spirit hath made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for you againſt ſuch wreſtling; becauſe hee hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to deſcribe</hi> Melchiſedec, <hi>or Chriſt to be a Tyth-taker.</hi> Leui <hi>indeede hath that Emphaticall Title, to be a Tyth-taker:</hi> Melchiſedec <hi>hath no more but</hi> (He.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No more but He. Is that the matter? but its that (Hee) to whom, what is ſaid of <hi>Leui,</hi> muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, applyed: elſe 1. the ſentence gapes: and 2. <hi>Paul</hi> failes in his compariſon. There, that is, in Leuiticall Prieſthood, men that dye, take Tythes: here he, of whom its teſtified that he liues, muſt not that (He) haue (takes Tythes) applyed vnto him? as verſ. 21. <hi>Theſe Priests are made without an oath: But this with an oath:</hi> What was this (with an oath) but made Prieſt?</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Melchiſedec tooke once; followes it that Chriſt muſt take euer? Apage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That but once you will neuer prooue. And 2. May not one Act tranſient, being Typicall, ſignifie a perpetuall act in Chriſt, as well as the manie En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trings of th'high Prieſt into the Holy of Holyes, Chriſts once entring into heauen? <hi>Proh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Chriſt by this meanes claimes from his Type.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Apage.</hi> How more Tythes from <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec,</hi> then kingdome from <hi>Dauid?</hi> His grand Title to Prieſthood, and kingdome, is Gods decree and ordination. The ſignification thereof in the Types, yet neceſſary it is, that th'Antitype ſhould
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133:22"/> anſwer exactly to the Type; <hi>vt ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>But thinkes any man they were due to</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec or <hi>his Prieſthood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Any man? I dare ſay thouſands after th'Apoſtle, and except your ſelfe all men of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Calvine; Quod debebat Abraham Deo, ſoluit in manum Melchiſedec.</hi> They were therefore due debt from <hi>Abraham. Ius ſacerdotij illius ſubindicat aeternae eſſe durationis: Hoc autem ideo additum eſt, ne videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur posterior lex (vt moris eſt) priori quicquam dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſſe. Calvin. ad Heb.</hi> 7. There was then a Law for their payment to <hi>Melchiſedec. Iunius ad Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec ab Abrahamo Decimas non dubitauit accipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, fretus authoritate Dei; et ex ea rite perfungens Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis officio.</hi> Authority then <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> had to take; therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> praecept to pay Tythes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> There was no praecept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> None read or expreſt in ſo many letters and ſyllables: Nor any for <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to vſe functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Prieſthood. Thinke wee therefore hee did it without calling?</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>The act was voluntary in</hi> Abraham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How vnderſtand you voluntary? willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed: ſo did <hi>Paul</hi> preach the Goſpel wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly: that Act of preaching was in <hi>Paul</hi> voluntary: yet<note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor 9.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Woe had beene vnto him if he had not preached the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>Not ſo; but voluntarie, as matter of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, courteſie and bountie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As ſome almes belike to the poore King of <hi>Salem:</hi> for ſuch you would haue all that's now payd to Miniſters of the Goſpel. But oppoſe you volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133:23"/> to matter of inioyned dutie? then ſay I, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo voluntary in <hi>Abraham,</hi> could not teſtifie his inferioritie to <hi>Melchiſedec.</hi> No payment, except of duty, is teſtimony of inferioritie.<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>Abrahams payment of Tythes to</hi> Melchiſedec, <hi>was testimonie of inferioritie;</hi> therefore it was payment of duty. You miſtake if you conceiue it ſaid, that all payments of dues imply inferioritie of the payer. Not ſo: But no payment, except of dutie, teſtifies th'inferiority of the payer. What haue we now to doe with Kings paying wages to ſeruants? and ſuch like prattle. Its ſtill true; except <hi>Abrahams</hi> payment to <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> had beene of duty, it could be no teſtimony of his inferiority. Compare <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5, 6.</p>
            <p>Obiect. <hi>They were not payde of all, nor of his owne, nor often. Therefore not due by any Law of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All vncertaine. <hi>Of all,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes. Gen.</hi> 14.20. that is, ſaith Maſter <hi>Calvine,</hi> reaſoning from cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the text, of all his owne ſubſtance, and that commonly: for it is likely, hee that had ſworne to<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>take nothing, from a thred to a ſhooe-latchet,</hi> for his owne enrichment, would at another mans coſt offer vnto God? It was a <hi>Piaculum</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> to offer vnto his God <hi>of that which coſt him nothing.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.24. And as great ſcandall had <hi>Abraham</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred amongſt thoſe Heathens, by performing his Deuotions at their charge, as by taking of theirs, for his owne enrichment. 2. But how followes the Argument? if but once, nor of all; <hi>Ergo,</hi> not by Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. q. d. Abel offered but once,</hi> for ought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares; <hi>Ergo,</hi> without law. And yet by faith hee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133:23"/> offered. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. therefore not without a word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melchiſedec tythed Abraham; if Tythes were not due, where is the Emphaſis of the phraſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely quite loſt: for it imparts a <hi>ius</hi> in <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to take; therefore a <hi>debitum</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi> to pay them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is all one as to ſay, a Tyth-taker for a Prieſt: Tythes and Priest-hood, are as inſeparable as kingdome and Tribute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Euen ſo. That deſcription of Chriſts Prieſthood by the <hi>ius</hi> of Tything, hangs in your teeth. Giue me a reaſon of that trope; putting <hi>Tyth-taking</hi> for <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and ſee if it enforce not my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. Prieſthood and Tythes are as inſeparable, as Kingdome and Tribute. <hi>But doe Tribute and Tythes match?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, in the point of inſeparability from their ſubiect: As Tribute to Kingdome; ſo Tythes to Prieſthood are inſeparable. Will you ſtretch your compariſon further? you wrong your Authour, and forget your rule; <hi>ſimilia claudicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how a good-yeare fell</hi> Abraham and <hi>Iacob vpon tenths without iniunction? Forſooth</hi> Iacob <hi>by</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams <hi>example:</hi> Abraham <hi>by ſpeciall direction from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By ſpeciall direction? likely ſome inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but had that direction the force of an iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? then was <hi>Abrahams</hi> act of duty, and not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For ſacrifices, their vſe held by tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By tradition? Now how a good-yeare
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133:24"/> comes tradition in to bee the ancient Rule of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? Tradition, ſelfe-deuiſed cuſtome, without a praecept from God. 2. Tradition wee yeeld it was, in a ſenſe, as matters of faith and worſhip were all traditionary, till the dayes of <hi>Moſes:</hi> that is, they were deliuered from father to ſonne, without wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: ſo was that, that <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>ſeed of the woman ſhould breake the Serpents head,</hi> &amp;c. In that ſenſe Tradition: but what is not alſo a diuine reuelation? So tradition that ſacrifices ſhould be offered: but was not the praecept extant for the matter of ſacrifices? of <hi>cleane not vncleane beasts.</hi> 2. for the qualitie; of the <hi>beſt,</hi> not of their <hi>refuſe?</hi> How elſe ſinned <hi>Cain</hi> in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a ſacrifice? And is not <hi>Abel</hi> ſaid,<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 11.4</note> 
               <hi>by faith to haue offered a better ſacrifice?</hi> and is there faith without a word of God?</p>
            <p>Thus I conclude. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> had ſinned, if they had not brought ſacrifices: <hi>Cain</hi> did ſinne in bringing ſuch a ſacrifice: therefore there was a Law for ſacrifices, and the qualitie of them; for the rule is of perpetuall truth,<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>Where is no Law, there is no transgreſsion.</hi> Likewiſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> had ſinned, if hee had not payde Tythes to <hi>Melchiſedec.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that bound <hi>Abraham</hi> to pay Tythes to him. For where is no Law, there can be no ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how followes it on all this ground layde, that Ministers muſt liue of Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they are miniſters of holy things; therefore muſt liue of Chriſts portion; and that Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Tythes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But that place.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>ſpeakes not of Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It will trouble you to prooue, that it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133:24"/> implies not Tythes, though it expreſſe them not: That <hi>(So)</hi> and <hi>(Chriſt hath ordayned)</hi> remit vs to Tythes, or elſe to no certeintie. 2. But <hi>quid hoc ad rem?</hi> That text is not, in this paſſage, alledged, to prooue Tythes our portion, ſaue onely vpon ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall; that Tythes are Chriſts portion. That granted, ſith Chriſt hath made his Portion, his Miniſters Portion, the Texts alledged will prooue Tythes the Miniſters: <hi>Deo gratias;</hi> I haue done with a Trifler. I come now to ſatisfie my learned friend in his <hi>quaere</hi> about this Text. Thus he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth is, that if we take the ſeuenth of th'Epistle to the Hebrewes as it is alone, without reference to whom it was written, and after what manner, and obſeruing how th' Apoſtle (as in other things) workes vpon</hi> the preſent opinions and ſtate of the Iewiſh Church, <hi>by that</hi> pia vafrities <hi>(as ſome call it) the Arguments for the right as</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Sclater <hi>hath reſolued them into Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call forme, are ſuch as he that anſwers them, might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the proofe of any Truth. Doubtleſſe, he that herein anſwers</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Sclater, <hi>anſwers more then all the reſt of, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Take wee it therefore with all references poſſibly imaginable; and conſider any circumſtance probably competent to be conſidered; yeeld alſo th' Apoſtle to vſe, if not that <hi>pia vafrities,</hi> yet his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in working vpon the preſent opinions of the Iewes; what I wonder, may any theſe references, or obſeruings affoord, to croſſe th'Argument heere founded. Particularize the references; 1. He writes to <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> become Chriſtians. 2. Confeſſedly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme in iudgement touching abrogation of Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133:25"/> Law; and adhaering too much to their firſt rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 3. opinioned, as truth ſeemes, that Ancient praecepts Moſaicall ſtill bound the conſcience, after exhibiting of the Meſſiah. What, to our maine, will all this affoord to nullifie or diſable the Argument here grounded? His <hi>pia vafrities,</hi> if it be conceited after <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> his working vpon aduantage of their miſconceits, and errours of iudgement, hath here I dare ſweare, neither vſe, nor footing. For what is in all this paſſage miſconceiued by thoſe Chriſtian Iewes? whereout <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſtrayne his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſts ſuperioritie, to Leuiticall Prieſts? <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 7.21</note> 
               <hi>ſweares him a Prieſt after order of</hi> Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec: And<note n="s" place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>without controuerſie, the leſſe is bleſſed of the greater;</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>To ſpeake as the thing is, Leui was tythed in the loynes of</hi> Abraham, ſauour any theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerations of <hi>Pauls</hi> working on miſconceites.</p>
            <p>His prudence it was to ground his concluſions on Scriptures, and Propoſitions thereof, confeſſed by Iewes as true; yet truely ſo confeſſed; and of force to affoord him, out of their reall truth, and intention of the inſpirer, whatſoeuer inference he makes from them: ſo was it our Sauiours, out of <hi>Moſes</hi> writings to conuince<note n="u" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 22.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>Sadduces,</hi> in th'<hi>Article of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> yet was there truth in his ground, and by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable ſequele iſſues his concluſion out of the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes extant in <hi>Moſes.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> at Athens al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth teſtimony of <hi>Aratus</hi> the Poet,<note n="w" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we acknowledge his prudence impleading them from their owne Authours: yet dare not thinke him ſo impiouſly <hi>vafer,</hi> as to lay for ground an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous conceit: or ſo imprudent a diſputer, as to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133:25"/> build his concluſion on a ground, from whence the Argument had not apparent deduction. I preſume, this curt anſwer affoords ſo learned and friendly an inquiſitor, large ſatisfaction. Proceede wee therefore to the other Arguments.</p>
            <p>I thought, you ſee I thought, I had ended; and that the mouth of all Calumnie againſt this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had beene ſtopped; when at laſt I am minded by a friend, that the <hi>grand Syllogiſmes labour of two foule maladies,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and begging of the Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet cannot be euidenced any change of tearmes, or ſo much as of affection of any tearme in the ſtate: neither is either propoſition tendred without proofe to any mans credulitie; nor without ſomething, <hi>prius</hi> and <hi>notius in ſe,</hi> and vertuall enough to inferre the concluſion. Faire anſwer expect to your excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; howſoeuer, carried with tartneſſe more then is meete, and eleuation no leſſe ſometime then mucte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſticall.</p>
            <p>This is the frame.</p>
            <p>The Portion due to Chriſts Prieſthood, is due to Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Tythes are the Portion due to Chriſts Prieſthood. <hi>Ergo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is thus prooued.</p>
            <p>The Portion due to <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Prieſthood, is due to Chriſts Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>Tythes are the Portion due to <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. <hi>Ergo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Propoſitions (you ſay) are both Sophiſticall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not propounded in fit tearmes to inferre the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion:
<pb facs="tcp:133:26"/> beſides, haue in them a begging of the quaeſtion, preſuming of that, which in good Diuinitie is not to bee granted. And th' aſſumptions are both falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why, I wonder, are the tearmes vnfit, beeing two of them the ſame without aequiuocation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the concluſion is propounded; and the <hi>medium</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, no whit homonymous, and applicable both to praedicate and ſubiect?</p>
            <p>Forſooth, <hi>the true tearmes are theſe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Stipend or Wages due to Chriſts Prieſthood, is due to Miniſters of the Goſpel.</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Stipend or Wages due to Melchiſedechs Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, is due to Chriſts Prieſthood.</hi> Sounds Stipend with you nothing but baſe Wages?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emendemus in Melius:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Remigius in Pſalmos.</note> hee was no Dunſe that obſerued, there is <hi>emendatio in peius.</hi> Theſe tearmes are neyther truer, nor true; nor fitter, nor fit for the quaeſtion: Truth is, fit for his purpoſe onely, who meanes to leaue the purpoſe, and to ſet vp a ſhadow for himſelfe to fight with. Could you, could any thinke, that in my tearme of Portion, which is part of Temporalties allotted, I ſhould intend Wages? ſuch as is payde to Hirelings, Maechanicall Artiſans, or men of like imployment: or if you take my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tearme of <hi>Praemium,</hi> or Recompence, was it intended, trow you, a Wages aequiualent to the Worke?</p>
            <p>I euer meant it an Honorarie, allotted by God, to be rendred from men, in acknowledgement of the vertue, excellencie, worth of Chriſts Prieſthood, and his Miniſters Worke, who are imployed by him in the commemoration and application thereof vnto
<pb facs="tcp:133:26"/> the people. This is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of that tearme: that other is <hi>vafra,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where now is my <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio principij?</hi> or what is that, ſo abhorrent from the grant of good Diuinitie? Forſooth, <hi>I preſume there is a ſet Stipend or Wages belonging to the Prieſthood of Christ, and Melchiſedec.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely I neuer preſumed it. Wages ſaid I euer in all my Sermon? The terme is ſtrange to me. Marry this I preſume, and yet am not preſumptuous, That there is a ſet or fixed Honorarie belonging to the Prieſthood of Chriſt, and <hi>Melchiſedec.</hi> Will your Reaſons force me to thinke otherwiſe? then I ſit downe.</p>
            <p>Thus they are. 1. <hi>Christ needes none.</hi> 2. <hi>Hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires none.</hi> 3. <hi>None can be aſsigned him anſwerable to his Worke, beeing a Worke of ſatisfaction for the ſinnes of the whole World, a Worke of infinite Merite.</hi> And for <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> and his Prieſthood; <hi>Sith,</hi> 1. <hi>None due to Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Sith Scripture ſilent for any proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of any ſuch thing.</hi> 3. <hi>Sith it affoords more then probabilitie to the contrarie: becauſe hee a King, therefore,</hi> 1. <hi>not needing it:</hi> 2. <hi>therefore bound ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to giue to his Subiects and Familie, then to take Wages from them: Yea,</hi> 3. <hi>Its euer counted baſe in a King, to take Stipend or Wages of Forreiners, or his owne Subiects.</hi> Ergo,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quorſum</hi> all this? what needes ſo much adoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong friends?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Its not Wages we enquire of, but the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norarie of the Prieſthood. And of it, who dares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uow, there is none due to Chriſts Prieſthood?</p>
            <p>How feare I, leaſt applying your Arguments to
<pb facs="tcp:133:27"/> that Concluſion, which is the onely you muſt inſiſt on, I ſhall expoſe them to ſcorne; and make them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſuch, as you affirme mine, weake as water, light as feathers, not worth ſtrawes, or the duſt adhaering to them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> What if <hi>Christ neede no honorarie to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from vs?</hi> therefore is none belonging to his Prieſthood? Though <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 50.9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>needed nor Bullocks nor Goates</hi> in Holocauſts, or Thanks-offerings, were they therefore not to bee rendred from <hi>Iewes?</hi> Though Chriſt needes not <hi>our Lands,</hi> or <hi>Liuings,</hi> or <hi>Liues,</hi> yet, in caſe of <hi>Confeſsion,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 10.37.</note> can they bee but impiouſly denyed him? Who knowes not as much as <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> in this caſe, that all our ſeruice of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Pſa. 16.2. Iob 22.2, 3</note> outward, redounds to ours, not to Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe? Belong they not therefore to our God? Chriſt needes not take: yet its our <hi>opus</hi> and <hi>vſus</hi> too to render him outward, inward ſeruice and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>When God calls to Iewes for <hi>Tythes</hi> vnder name of<note n="e" place="margin">Mal. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>his owne,</hi> that there might be <hi>meat in his Houſe,</hi> no man is ſo mad to thinke of the liuing God, as is fabled or ſtoried of th'Idol <hi>Bel</hi> and the <hi>Dragon.</hi> Yet muſt there be meate in his Houſe <hi>for them to whom the ministration of his ſeruice was then committed.</hi> And though Chriſt, <hi>for his owne Perſon,</hi> now needes not this Honorarie, yet needes hee it in his Deputes and Aſſignes, <hi>whom he hath</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>put in his ſtead,</hi> to commemorate and apply the vertues of his aeternall Prieſthood, and to keepe in life and being, the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Prieſthood, exerciſed by all Chriſtians in the ſtate of this life.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:27"/>
            <p>And doth he not require it?<note n="g" place="margin">Pro. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>Honour God with <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>2</label> thy ſubſtance, and with the chiefe of all thy increaſe;</hi> that he requires.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>Render Carnals to them that ſowe Spirituals:</hi> That hee requires.<note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Count Presbyters wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honour;</hi> thats apertly the Honorarie wee now ſpeake of. For Wages, or hyre, as you ſtyle and explane it, let it not be once named in this quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, as becommeth Saints: out vpon that baſe conceit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>None can be aſsigned him, anſwerable to his worke.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>3</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> True as Goſpell: nor Wages nor Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie aequiualent to his merite.<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 116.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Quid retribuam?</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> Poſſibly nothing aequable to Gods bountie; <hi>our goodneſſe extends not to him:</hi> yet there was <hi>Poculum ſalutis,</hi> which <hi>hee tooke and offered</hi> in teſtimonie of thankefulneſſe, for ſo many and great things done to his Soule. When <hi>Iacob</hi> according to his Vow erected th'Altar<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 35.1.</note> at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and (who queſtions?) payde Tythes to God that had kept him; dreames any man hee meant it to the Lord as a Wage for his Worke, in ſafe-guarding his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Honorarie aequiualent to ſuch merites? <hi>Lord, I am</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> 
               <hi>leſſe then all thy Goodneſſe and Truth, which thou haſt ſhowne me, &amp;c.</hi> Why doubt wee that it was a dutie in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſuch as found acceptance with God? Reade alſo that excellent Bleſſing and <hi>Prayer of</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1. Chr. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> what time hee deliuers his owne and the Peoples Offerings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards building the Temple: It will appeare true which you ſay; the Honorarie was not worthie the Lord, yet due to him from <hi>Dauid,</hi> and from the People.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133:28"/>
            <p>What need I now proceed to particular anſwer, to what concernes <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> Prieſthood? The Scripture affoords more then probabilitie, praegnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of proofe for an Honorarie due to that Royall Prieſt, and Prieſthood. Neither was it baſe, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable to that King of <hi>Salem,</hi> to be inueſted as well in the Honorarie, as in th'Office of that Prieſthood. Will you now ioyne in the cloſe for the Honorarie, as you profeſſe to doe vpon ſuppoſall of Wages? If <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> receiued Wages, then you graunt, it ſhould be perpetuall. What if he receiued th'Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie, will you then graunt, muſt you not graunt, that it ſhould be perpetuall? <hi>Iungamus dexteras.</hi> This little explication hath wrought our harmonie in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the maine.</p>
            <p>Muſt wee yet buckle about th'aſſumptions? What thinke you? are they yet <hi>both falſe;</hi> and againe, you ſay <hi>falſe,</hi> twice falſe, if my portion be not <hi>Merces,</hi> but <hi>Honorarium?</hi> What if there be <hi>no proportion betwixt the worth of Chriſts Priesthood, and Tythes?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the Honorarie of his Prieſthood? What though no proportion betweene the <hi>ſpirituall things wee ſowe,</hi> and the carnall, wee reape from the people? <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.11.</note> Carnals no Honorarie due to Miniſterie for Spirituals? What though no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the<note n="p" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Quiet and Godlineſſe and Honestie we liue in by meanes of Kings,</hi> and the<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Tribute and Custome</hi> wee render to thoſe Earthly Gods? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the Honorarie of Regalitie? I ſay not yet as you to me, <hi>Apageſis.</hi> Yet I aduiſe, make no ſuch inferences. How vaine are they? who ſees not their vanitie? To ſay truth, how were they Honoraries, if
<pb facs="tcp:133:28"/> there might be found meere paritie or proportion betwixt them?</p>
            <p>As to what is talked of <hi>Abrahams paying Tythes, as Wages, to Melchiſedec,</hi> and the diſproofe thereof: Alas, its naught to purpoſe. We talke not of Wages. Whether the ſcrupulous Gentleman you mention, be the Cauiller I deale with, in my review, I know not: but finde you both iumping on the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and Reaſons in refutation. I referre you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for farther anſwer, to what is ſaid to him in my replie: And for more full ſatisfaction, to what is ſcholied by my much reuerenced friend &amp; <hi>quondam</hi> Collegue M. <hi>Mountague,</hi> in his anſwer to M. <hi>Selden.</hi> Yet, that I ſeeme not ſlightfull of ſuch a friend, or willing to leape ouer Reaſons for defect of anſwer, Thus briefely to your Reaſons bent to prooue, Tythes not payde by <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> of dutie, or as you would bee vnderſtood, <hi>ex debito Iustitiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>No Couenant betwixt</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec: <hi>Ergo not payde ex</hi> debito Iuſtitiae. 2. <hi>This act of</hi> Abraham <hi>was an act of Pietie and Deuotion; Ergo,</hi> not of Iuſtice. 3. <hi>Had it beene impoſed on</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>by Law, all the Grace and commendation of it had beene loſt: for Law and Grace fight.</hi> 4. Iacobs <hi>Tything, being of the ſame Nature with</hi> Abrahams, <hi>was voluntarie, ſaue for his Vow.</hi> 5. <hi>Scripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely auowes</hi> Melchiſedec <hi>had no Law to take;</hi> Ergo, <hi>nor</hi> Abraham <hi>command to pay Tythes.</hi> Thus is your Breuiarie.</p>
            <p>But doth onely Couenant and Compact breede <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>1</label> Debts of Iuſtice? Doth not alſo Commandement?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133:29"/> Doe not Benefits? &amp;c. What Compact I wonder twixt Parents and Children, to oblige the Childe to obedience and maintenance? A Commandement there is<note n="r" place="margin">Exod. 20. Matth 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>to honour,</hi> that is, to ſuſtaine the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent;</hi> and its<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 6.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> without Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>to obey in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>2</label> What? <hi>Becauſe an act of Pietie, therefore not of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Know you none but ciuill Iuſtice paſſing betwixt man and man? Haue you forgotten, that there is <hi>vniuerſalis Iuſtitia,</hi> binding to render <hi>Cuique quod ſuum eſt?</hi> Not onely to Neighbour and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but vnto God, what belongs vnto him? Is not Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a part of this Iuſtice? Is it not exacteſt Iuſtice, which bindes to render dutie to our God? Why make you things fight, that are coordinate or ſubal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>3</label> And looſe <hi>our Offices their Grace, which are done by commandement?</hi> Had not <hi>Abraham</hi> his<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 22.2</note> 
               <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> to offer <hi>Iſaac?</hi> or euer paſſed act from him, by which hee receiued more grace or commendation from God, then this of offering his ſonne <hi>Iſaac?</hi> Gaue not this <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Verſ. 12.16.</note> 
               <hi>hent</hi> to that excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, and ratifying of enlarged Bleſſing? By this, wonne he not the ſtyle of<note n="w" place="margin">Iam. 2.23</note> 
               <hi>Gods friend,</hi> the greateſt <hi>encomium</hi> God euer gaue man? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you not the vſuall <hi>Quaere,</hi> whether muchneſſe of obligation winne not grace to the performance? or the reſolution? <hi>Vbi maior obligatio, maior accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio;</hi> becauſe <hi>melior eſt obedientia quàm victimae.</hi> I ſpare cenſure of your miſ-applying Scriptures, in this and other paſſages. I wonder, I ſorrow at it.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133:30"/> But am vowed to keepe cloſe to ſubſtance of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            <p>And was it not in <hi>Iacob</hi> an act of Iuſtice, ſetting <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>4</label> apart conſideration of his Vow? <hi>No: For hee makes Tythes the matter of his Vow, which hee ought not to haue done, if they had beene enioyned by any Law of God.</hi> You will not ſay ſo of th'other part of his Vow, as I ſuppoſe.</p>
            <p>But meane you good earneſt? Thinke you it ſoothly true which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith? <hi>Impium fuiſſet Iacobo vovere Decimas, ſi abſolutè fuiſſet obligatus eas ſoluere:</hi> Is it your opinion, That no Vow may paſſe on any matter, whereto wee are obliged <hi>abſolutely,</hi> that is, by peremptorie Praecept? when vnder <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Princes, Priests, People, made</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Neh. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Couenant, and entred into a Curſe, to walke in Gods Law, giuen by</hi> Moſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Suppoſe you they erred in the matter of their Vow? were they not abſolutely bound ſo to doe? were they impious in ſo vowing? when vnder <hi>Ieremie, They</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 34.8, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>couenant to manumit their ſeruants according to the Law;</hi> miſtake they the matter of a Vow? were they impious, in ſo obliging themſelues? Is it ſo impious, to adde to the Bond of Praecept the Obligation of a Vow?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laxè,</hi> you ſay, ſuch Promiſes may be called Vowes; properly not Vowes. <hi>A Vow properly taken, is of ſome caeremonious worke in the Old Testament; of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and corporall exerciſe in the New; which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer affirmes to be Morall duties, doth himſelfe more iniurie, then he is aware of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sir, you minded mee in the ingreſſe, of Sophiſtrie. Truly, truly, I haue forgotten much of
<pb facs="tcp:133:31"/> it; and count that forgetfulneſſe halfe as vertuous as the Athenians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Yet prettie well remember my Logique Rules; amongſt which, this was wont to be one Authentique: <hi>A negatione vnius ſpeciei ad tollendum genus vniuerſum non valet conſequentia.</hi> Its no man, therefore no animal; thinke you that good conſequence? Its no Vow of things left to our choiſe to doe, or not to doe; therefore no Vow at all? ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you that good conſequence? then farewell all Logique. The Act of Vowing paſſeth as lawfully, as properly on things commanded, as on thoſe left Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie. What vſe Vowes of inioyned duties haue, you are not to learne; and may ſee remembred by me, in anſwer to that Argument of <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Giue vs now what differences you pleaſe of one and other ſort of Vowes, whiles religious promiſe may lawfully be made to God of performing what he commands, the Argument will neuer proceede. Tythes were vowed by <hi>Iacob,</hi> therefore not commanded of God. Thus I conceiue. A Vow properly ſo called, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious promiſe made vnto God; is of two ſorts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to diuerſitie of the matter: There is a Vow of things commanded; and a Vow of things arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Both are properly Vowes, howeuer differenced by ſubſtance, or circumſtance: therefore proceedes no argument from negation of one <hi>ſpecies,</hi> to remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall of the vniuerſall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad. </seg>5</label> Expreſſe Scripture you haue, auouching <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> payment to haue beene without iniunction, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5, 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Expreſſe Scripture? then lay I my hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my mouth, neuer more to open it to that aſſertion.
<pb facs="tcp:133:31"/> But are you ſure Scripture ſpeakes it, and ſpeakes it expreſſely? When <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 7.5, 6,</note> 
               <hi>Leui had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to tythe his Brethren,</hi> denyed hee <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> had like warrant to tythe <hi>Abraham?</hi> Say, I beſeech you, in ſober ſadneſſe; ſay as Conſcience dictates: as the Text leades you. Is this (indeede) made diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to prooue ſuperioritie of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> to <hi>Leui;</hi> that <hi>Leui</hi> tythed by Law, <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> without Law? Where doth the Scripture expreſſe, or but imply that? yea, doth it not imply the contrarie? What intends the Apoſtle, in comparing the tything of <hi>Leui</hi> with that of <hi>Melchiſedec?</hi> but apertly to proue <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> ſuperior to <hi>Leui,</hi> euen in this honour of Tything? or trow you, this prooues a ſuperioritie in <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> to take without Law, whereas <hi>Leui</hi> takes according to Law? Say, I pray, whether is the baſer Tenure? that by Law; or that by Curteſie, and at Will? I ſhould thinke, that at Will. And if <hi>Leui</hi> tooke by Law, <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> but of Curteſie, <hi>Leui</hi> ſure had the preheminence. Farre be it, the Apoſtle ſhould bring argument to ouerthrow his intention. Truth is, the compariſon there entred, lyes onely in the Subiects tythed, not in the ground of Tything. <hi>Leui</hi> tythes Brethren: <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> the Patriarch and chiefe Father of thoſe Brethren, is therefore more excellent then <hi>Leui;</hi> inaſmuch, as the very Prince of their race is ſubiected to his Prieſthood, and bound to render the Honorarie thereof.</p>
            <p>If you now ſhall aske, what <hi>Paul</hi> meanes to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Commandement or Warrant giuen <hi>Leui</hi> to tythe his Brethren? thus I ſhould conceiue: That
<pb facs="tcp:133:32"/> whereas Tythes originally belonged to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, typed in <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> a Law was neceſſarie to aſſigne them to <hi>Leui,</hi> and to make him capable of that honour; inaſmuch, as without this ſpeciall Law, <hi>Leui</hi> could neuer haue made clayme or title to that honour, which firſtly was ſetled on the Prieſthood of another Order. So, that vpon the point, the difference ſtands not in Tything by Law, and without Law; or, better to expreſſe my ſelfe; Law is not here oppoſed to no Law, or <hi>iniunction to vltroneouſneſſe of Tything;</hi> but rather <hi>this Law</hi> for <hi>Leui,</hi> to <hi>originall right: Melchiſedec</hi> tything <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> by Right, or Law originall: <hi>Leui</hi> his Brethren, by Law ſpeciall, and graunt for the time: To which end, particular Law was requiſite, to inueſt that Prieſthood in the <hi>ius</hi> of Tything, which before was ſetled, as on the foundation in the Prieſthood, after another Order.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument hath ground, <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.6. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.9. where wee reade thus. <hi>Let him that is inſtructed, make his inſtructer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all his goods.</hi> And, <hi>Elders that rule well, are worthy of double honour, eſpecially they which labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> And, <hi>Honour God with thy ſubſtance, and with the chiefe of all thine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi> Out of which Scriptures, thus wee reaſon: If there be a portion to be ſet out vnto God and his Miniſters, out of all and euery the temporall goods of euery one inſtructed, and no certaine portion to bee found in Scripture, but Tythes; then are Tythes the portion allotted by Gods Word, to Miniſters, for their ſeruice. But there is a portion
<pb facs="tcp:133:32"/> to be ſet out vnto God and his Miniſters, out of all the temporall goods of euery one inſtructed, and no other certainty mentioned in Scripture. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Tythes are the portion allotted by Gods Word to Miniſters for their ſeruice.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of the propoſition depends vpon this ground, That ſome certaintie is by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture allotted to Miniſters for their ſeruice. Hereof if any demaund proofe, let him conſider theſe: 1. The Lord allotted a certaintie vnto firſt borne, and Leuites. And thinke wee it probable, hee would leaue Miniſters of the Goſpel to a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie indeterminate? 2. In other caſes th'Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment goes current. The Lord preſcribes for the old Tabernacle all things neceſſarie, euen to the Beeſome and Aſh-panne; not a Pinne in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, but what hath his praeſcript from God. Of this wee may ſay, its not a Pinne, but a <hi>Clavus Trabalis,</hi> one of the maſter Nayles in our Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. And thinke wee his Word ſo ſufficient, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely exact for all neceſſarie praeſcripts, yea, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, concerning Worſhip, Gouernment, any thing; and this onely, a matter of ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, left vnpraeſcribed?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if no certaintie, in this kinde, can be found in Scripture, how wilt thou bee able to ſhare out vnto God, his portion in faith? ſo that thou mayeſt bee able to ſay, I haue giuen the Lord that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Goods, which hee requireth of mee. Can wee doubt, whether God hath reſerued in Chriſtians poſſeſſions, his ſanctified portion? Reade, <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.5. Forſooth the Magiſtrates deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb facs="tcp:133:33"/> ſhall in this point be the leuell and rule of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Then muſt thou bee able to ſhew, that God hath made Magiſtrates in this point his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, which is vnlikely, <hi>vt ſupra.</hi> Suppoſe Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates make no prouiſion, as hath befallen many ſtates of the Church; imagine them Sacrilegiouſly rapinous; where is then the direction for thy Faith? Suppoſe they ſhall allow <hi>Micha's</hi> allowance, wilt thou therewith reſt content? then haue our Lay-Parſons Faith well guided, Conſciences rectified.<note n="x" place="margin">Iud. 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>Tenne Sheckles of Siluer, and a Meales meate, and Liuerie,</hi> they affoord Sir <hi>Iohn.</hi> In Faith thinke wee? Surely, according to the Magiſtrates pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion. And why blame wee any more impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Parſons, for ſo ſcant allowance? Perhaps, becauſe not competent. Yea, but the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate thinkes it competent. And that is, in this caſe, the Line of Faith. <hi>Credam? non ſi mihi, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Minor:</hi> For the firſt part, ſee, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.6. In which place, yee haue it in ſo many tearmes: <hi>Let him that is inſtructed, make his instructer partaker of all his goods.</hi> For the other Branch of it, That no other portion certaine is to bee found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; I meane, which hath not apparent ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomething peculiar to the ſtate of People vnder <hi>Leui,</hi> as Firſt fruites, ſhare of other Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; will appeare to any man, that will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to enter induction of particulars. And may I not then conclude, Tythes are the portion allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:133:33"/> vs by the Word of God? Yea, what if I ſhould ſay, Tythes are in ſome of theſe places more then obliquely pointed at? What meanes the Apoſtle to call for maintenance vnto Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, vnder the tearme of double honour? For that <hi>by</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>honour,</hi> hee there meanes mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the reaſon annexed will make a blinde man ſee. Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> hauing deliuered his iudgement of the place, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. <hi>Bring all my Tythes into the Store-houſe,</hi> in theſe tearmes, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae populis Praeceptum est dare Decimas,</hi> allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth praeſently this place for proofe. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Elders must haue double honour.</hi> 2. What meanes the Apoſtle by that Epithete (double) annexed to honour? Say ſome, large and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. But why double, rather then treble, if hee meant large at large? Doth hee not rather, in that phraſe of ſpeech, ſend vs to conſider the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion of the firſt borne,<note n="z" place="margin">Numb. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>into whoſe roome</hi> Leui <hi>was aſſumed?</hi> and that which made their portion double, in likelyhood was Tythes; as may hereafter, on a new inquirie, perhaps ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>What ſayth my learned friend to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? may it paſſe currant? <hi>All may be granted, without praeiudice to your Aduerſaries aſſertion, foraſmuch as theſe wordes are left out, which are energeticall, and wherein the whole ſtate of the Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion lyeth; which are, one onely ſet particular and perpetuall portion. For ſay, that ſome certaintie be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted by Scripture to Ministers, for their ſeruice; yea, that it is to be ſet out of all and euery the temporall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:133:34"/> goods of euery one inſtructed; and that there bee no certaintie expreſſed, but Tythes; and Tythes bee the portion, for the preſent, allotted by Gods Word for the Ministers ſeruice: what is all this to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if this certaintie bee alterable in it owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and that another (that being remooued) may without ſinne, bee placed in the roome and ſtead thereof, the contrarie whereof, is not by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prooued? for all that is, or can bee concluded thereof, is this, that Tythes are the portion allotted by Gods Word to Ministers (of the Goſpel) for their ſeruice; which no man doubteth of. The quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, whether they be the ſole and perpetuall Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea, or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sir, in my Sermon, when I vttered and penned it, I dealt with Layickes; wittie enough, ſome of them, to iudge of a Conſequence, though not much skilled in forme: I haue now to deale with a Clericke (too popular I feare mee) and will affoord him forme praeciſely; yet with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſo, that hee giue mee leaue regularly to chooſe my tearmes. I like not your mending, it is (for I know you are a prouerbiall man) too Tinker-like. You ſhall haue termes, ſuch as due forme affoords, moſt energeticall, and termes explicated, that you may ſee I meane not to double. Categorically thus.</p>
            <p>That portion, that's to ſay, determinate quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of Peoples Temporall ſubſtance, which God hath allotted to Miniſters of the Goſpel, for their ſeruice, is that which of dutie belongs vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:133:34"/>
            <p>But Tythes are that determinate quantitie of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples temporalties which God hath allotted Miniſters of the Goſpel for their ſeruice. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps I haue not yet ſufficiently explaned my ſelfe. Sure its more for lacke of words then good meaning: Let mee then in another particular par or parallel to this, expreſſe mine intention.</p>
            <p>The determinate quantitie of time which God hath reſerued and ſanctified to his ſeruice vnder the new Teſtament, is that which of neceſſarie dutie muſt be rendred him.</p>
            <p>But the ſeuenth of Time, is that determinate quantitie which God hath reſerued and ſanctified to himſelfe, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe twinnes of Morall duties I willingly chooſe to combine, as well for that I finde no munerall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teintie (which yet is greateſt) in any Gods morall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſaue in theſe two of Time and Subſtance; as alſo becauſe, as thoſe of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> they weepe and laugh, ſtand and fall together. I may adde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this of Gods Time affoords that of his reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſubſtance explication reciprocally, as that of Subſtance doth ſupport to his Time.</p>
            <p>What ſay you now, doe you grant all? or want you your energeticall termes of onely and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Why more I wonder for Gods ſubſtance then for his Time? will it not follow? no other therefore ſolely this; And by Gods word allotted, therfore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually and vnalterably to be rendered; I praeſume it will for Gods Time; why not alſo for his ſubſtance?</p>
            <p>What vſe now of your limitations and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Allotment for the praeſent, and for perpetuitie;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133:35"/> of alterableneſſe in it owne nature, and not in it owne nature. Apply them, if you dare, to the point of Time, as you doe to that of Subſtance. And tell me if your greateſt admirers blot not you, as they haue done vs poore Tything-men, out of their booke of the righteous.</p>
            <p>But <hi>dic ſodes,</hi> what meane you in ſaying th'allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is alterable in it owne Nature? What? that inſtitution onely and command determines their payment to be dutie; and that the office of Tything is <hi>bonum</hi> onely <hi>quia praeceptum.</hi> For my part I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not. There are moralities ſuch by inſtitution onely and by Law of God poſitiue. Suppoſe now; if you will, their dueneſſe founded onely on <hi>Law poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue;</hi> will you inferre, therefore alterable by man? As if I ſhould aske, whether becauſe another day is of it owne Nature, ſetting apart conſideration of Gods allotment, ordinable to Gods ſeruice, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſeuenth may be changed: or whether, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our two Sacraments are in <hi>their owne Nature</hi> alterable, and other elements, for any thing that is in the Nature of theſe now inſtituted, might be ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in ſtead of theſe, therefore man hath power to alter them. I ſhould thinke (ſuch is my ſimplicitie) Gods Law and Ordinance perpetually bindes to theſe, and no other: though there bee nothing in their Nature repugnant to ſubſtitution of others. What God hath fixed, let no man mooue. What he hath determinately praeſcribed, who may dare alter. Gods ordinance is the Ancienteſt <hi>boundarie; A curſe is to him who praeſumes to remooue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea Sir, doe you grant all? Saith God in his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133:35"/> word to Miniſters as once to Leui, <hi>I haue giuen them Tythes for the ſeruice they doe mee in the Goſpel?</hi> Shall any doubt whether th'allotment be of aequall endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with the ſeruice? or that th' honorarie may be changed, ſo long as the Seruice continues? Thus briefely. As to Leui they were aſſigned <hi>for</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>his Seruice in the Tabernacle,</hi> and were vnalterably to be rendred ſo long as the Tabernacle ſtood: So to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel they muſt ſtand, vpon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, ſo long as their Euangelicall Seruice conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, that is, as I ſuppoſe, ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endureth. Except perhaps you can euidence they are exceptiuely or diſiunctiuely only allotted; Tythes or ſome other thing in roome or ſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which who will vndertake to euidence by the word of God?</p>
            <p>Our third reaſon hath ground on <hi>Leuit.</hi> 27.28. <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.25. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. where we reade thus. <hi>Euery thing ſeparate from common vſe, is moſt holy vnto the Lord:</hi> And <hi>it is a ſnare to deuoure holy things, and after the vow to enquire</hi> And, <hi>thou which abhorrest Idols, committest thou Sacriledge?</hi> And, <hi>yee haue robbed mee.</hi> Out of which Scriptures thus wee reaſon.</p>
            <p>The portion ſeparated from common vſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods worſhip vnder the new Teſtament, is that portion allotted by Gods word to Miniſters for their ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Tythes are of that portion ſo ſeparate. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is thus prooued: becauſe the detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or alienation of things ſo conſecrated, is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. That this may the better appeare, It will be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:133:36"/> worth the while, to conſider briefely what Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is, which out of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Zanchius, Vrſine,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we may thus briefely deſcribe. Sacriledge is the taking away of things Sacred, that is, deputed to holy vſes, or the maintenance and furtherance of Gods worſhip. The matter about which this theft is conuerſant, are things conſecrated to God: of which are two ſorts. Some, which God himſelfe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reſeruation to himſelfe, or by expreſſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date hath hallowed to himſelfe; ſome, which man hath hallowed and ſeparated from common vſe: wherein is alſo acknowledged by moſt prudent, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret motion of God inclining to ſuch conſecration. Of both reade, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 27, 28, 29, 30.</p>
            <p>That which makes vp the nature of Sacriledge, is alienating or detaining things thus hallowed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning them to common vſe. Thus is the Reaſon. The alienating or detaining of any thing ſeparate from common vſe, is Sacriledge. But detainment or alienating of Tythes, is the detaining or aliening of things thus ſeparate. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the propoſitions, theſe anſwers I haue partly read, partly heard in conference. 1. Vnderſtand it, ſay ſome, of things conſecrate by Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No word of God forceth to ſuch limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At building of Tabernacle, was there any law of God particular to contribute? Why then runnes the tenour thus? <hi>Euery man whoſe</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 35.5.</note> 
               <hi>heart is willing, let him bring, Gold, Siluer, Goates haire,</hi> &amp;c. And euen of voluntarie and votarie conſecrations both <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeake. And, was it not free to <hi>Ananias</hi> to conſecrate or not, otherwiſe then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:133:36"/> generall lawes of pietie or charitie might ſway him? <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Whiles it remained, was it not thine owne? And after it was ſold, was it not in thy power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet was <hi>Ananias</hi> his detainement, Sacriledge: by circumſtances of the Text, and conſent of beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters. He is taxed by <hi>Peter,</hi> not onely for ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but for theeuiſh and clancular ſurreption of part of the price, verſ. 3. And ſaith Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the word; <hi>Ad Sacrilegium etiam acceſsit diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia &amp; hypocriſis.</hi> There was then Sacriledge in his detainement, though dedication was voluntarie. <hi>Centuriat: Cent.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Ambroſ. Ser.</hi> 9. <hi>Dum ex eo quod promiſerat, partem ſubtrahit, ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gij ſimul condemnatur &amp; fraudis; Sacrilegij, quod De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in Pollicitatione fefellerat, fraudis quod, &amp;c.</hi> They are ſtrange <hi>quaeres</hi> rayſed by giddie ſpirits, deſirous to free themſelues from ſtroke of this Argument; 1. As whether Sacriledge be a ſinne in theſe times of reformation; their meaning is, whether there bee any poſſibility of a Chriſtians falling into the ſinne of Sacriledge, otherwiſe then by defiling his body with the fleſh, or depriuing God of the honour im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately belonging vnto him. A quaeſtion, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, in theſe times ſomewhat diſputable; wherein the very matter of Sacriledge is almoſt annihilated. It calls to mind the teares of <hi>Alexander</hi> in the known ſtory, ſhedde vpon remembrance of his father <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> frequent victories, and conqueſts ſo large, as there ſeemed no matter left for his ambition to work vpon. How doth their couetouſneſſe mourne, and their hearts languiſh, that there is left them ſo little a gleaning, after the great harueſt of their praedeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:133:37"/> yet how gape they after that little prey vpon holy things, yet vnſurprized? We liue in a free ſtate; giue me leaue freely to ſpeake my minde. In my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I thinke it true, the clamours againſt Biſhops calling, and things appendent thereto, hath had no other ſource, then popular enuy at theſe fat holy morſels, which yet remaine vndeuoured, could they but calme conſcience, grumbling, I dare ſay, in many againſt th'attempt, and ſway ſupreame Authoritie, the iudgement threatned to the poſteritie of <hi>Eli,</hi> would ſoone be our fate; <hi>To</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.36.</note> 
               <hi>bow downe to our Lay-masters for a piece of ſiluer, and a morſell of bread, that we might be appointed to one of the Prieſts offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, with conſcience they haue taken order reaſonable; Sacriledge none, except ſpirituall, can now bee committed; matter of that ſinne, there is none; for God, in their opinion, hath reſerued to himſelfe no portion of earthly things: neither doth mans votarie or voluntary deuotion, giue him ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure in any thing, how piouſly ſo euer conſecrated. Belike then, Sacriledge there can be none vnder the new Teſtament: for there is nothing <hi>de iure,</hi> ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God. Once impleading the ſinne of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I was admoniſhed by a graue Praeſbyter, to beware of multiplying ſinnes; making more ſinnes then God had made; me thinkes I may remember him and his adhaerents; to take heede, how they leſſen the number, or miniſh the quantitie of ſinnes ſo heinous. Is there no Sacriledge vnder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel? Can none be committed in dayes of new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about things conſecrated vnto God? <hi>Genera
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:133:37"/> peccatorum minuuntur.</hi> Bleſſe your ſelues you Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, and carnall Goſpellers in this; feede your ſelues without feare on things, as wee ſay, conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God. You cannot now bee Sacrilegious; no more (and yet I dare ſay ſo much) then you can be Idolatrous, murtherous, luxurious. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in vaine (and I thinke he ſaid it to men of this mould) thou <hi>that abhorreſt Idols, committeſt thou Sacriledge? Rom.</hi> 2. Bluſh for ſhame at conceits ſo prophane, and thinke it trueſt of this glutted couetouſneſſe, which <hi>Iob</hi> long ſince ſpake of the generall; <hi>Hee hath deuoured ſubstance,</hi> but the Lord ſhall cauſe him to <hi>vomite it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond reſtraint ſome haue thus giuen to the propoſition; vnderſtand it, ſay they, of alienating things conſecrated without errour: that is, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of true worſhip of the true God. Well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, let it be ſo limited, though with faire proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and conſent of no ſmall Clerks, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the contrary. <hi>Keckerman:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Syſt. polit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Princeps iure non poteſt res ſacras it bona cultui diuino etiam in genere destinata, etiam ea quae ſuperstitioſo cultui ferviunt, in vſum profanum transferre.</hi> But grant the limitation. Can we not aſſume thus much of our Tythes? that they haue beene conſecrated to maintaine pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Vnderſtand it ſay ſome with theſe exceptions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Except in caſe of the Churches ſuperfluitie. And this exception hath this ground. Contentment with neceſſaries is required of Miniſters; for <hi>Moſes</hi> cryes <hi>ſufficit</hi> at building of the Tabernacle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> What word of God or found reaſon giues
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:133:38"/> libertie to alien ſeeming ſuperfluities of miniſters, rather then of other Subiects? ſpake <hi>Paul</hi> to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters onely when he ſayde, <hi>Let</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 13.5</note> 
               <hi>your conuerſation be without couetouſneſſe, and bee content with things praeſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Moſes</hi> onely ſtayes addition, of more, returnes or aliens nothing of what was brought by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, no not though there were an ouerplus.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yea, howeuer in this contribution to building of the Tabernacle, hee proclaimes a <hi>ſufficit,</hi> yet when he glanceth vpon the maintenance of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, you haue him praying God for abundance. <hi>Bleſſe O Lord his ſubstance. Deut.</hi> 33.11.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But yeeld the exception; In what caſe, in what times, may we not, with that limit, aſſume of Tythes?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their ſecond exception is, when alienation is neceſſary for preſeruation of the Church. In ſuch caſe<note n="e" place="margin">2. Reg. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiahs practiſe,</hi> may it not be imitated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Perhaps yes: ſo you keepe to your pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: and inferre not too farre. View therefore 1. the matter of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his alienation; you ſhall find it to be of things belonging rather <hi>to the ornaments of Gods worſhip,</hi> then to the <hi>maintenance of the miniſtery.</hi> 2. Take it into your ſerious conſideration; whether an action mutuall, or relatiue, ſuch as theſe are paſſing betwixt the giuer and receiuer, may not be in <hi>caſu,</hi> on the one ſide lawfull, on th'other, ſinnefull; As if I ſhould aske; may I not without ſinne in perill of life, and to auoide violence iuſtly feared, deliuer my purſe to a Thiefe? or doth not the Thiefe ſinne in receiuing, or deteining it? We will ſuppoſe <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:133:38"/> to haue done lawfully, in deliuering the <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Ornaments of the Temple to the King of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria,</hi> thereby to redeeme himſelfe and Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from his violence. But can you ſuppoſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhur</hi> leſſe then Sacrilegious in accepting, or detay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them? For euer I bleſſe his zeale, who to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme Chriſtian Captiues, would exchange his ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Chalice, for wood: yet ſhall curſe to hell him, who driues to this exigent, and thinke his crueltie, or couetouſnes no other then Sacrilegious. Though therefore neceſſitie perhaps may exempt ſuch alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from crime of Sacriledge on the part of the deliuerer, yet is not the action in all parts void of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge; yea, cannot be excuſed, on the receiuers behalfe, of prophane irreuerence, and irreligion to Godward. Goe now and triumph you Heluoes of holy things, ſample your ſelues from <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> But know, he is Sacrilegious, whoſoeuer accepts or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines things holy to God, howſoeuer percaſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deliuered into his poſſeſſion from hands of the rightfull Owners. 3. Can wee but thinke <hi>Hezekiah</hi> minded as<note n="f" place="margin">1. Kin. 14 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>Rehoboam</hi> practiſed? to reſtore what neceſſitie forced him to decay? Reade the ſtorie: perhaps you may bethinke your ſelues of reſtitution. 4. Let vs yeeld to neceſſitie; the force of it is great, to legitimate for the time, what nothing els can war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. May retaining ſuch things in that caſe aliened, be excuſed from Sacriledge, neceſſitie ceaſing? I aske your iudgement. <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſhew bread was made common to</hi> Dauid <hi>and his companie in extremitie:</hi> might it therefore be perpetually commoned?</p>
            <p>Their laſt exception: when Princes haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133:39"/> other means to remunerate ſubiects, faithfull in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeruices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What, I wonder in ſuch caſe, layes open Church goods to will of Princes, rather then the goods of common ſubiects? Thus I reaſon and leaue them. Priuate goods of Subiects, Magiſtrates may not alien from them for recompence of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: much leſſe may the Lords Portion be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to ſuch vſe. <hi>Pharao</hi> King of Aegypt, and <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> his Viceroy, giue immunitie to <hi>poſſeſsions of</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 47.22.</note> 
               <hi>Priests,</hi> when elſe the whole land is ſeized for the King: perſwaded (I ſuppoſe) things Sacred to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ought at no hand be violated. Thus then the propoſition is cleare as it was propounded. Yeeld we it yet with theſe limits and exceptions, as many as haue but ſhew of reaſon to ſupport them; and thus conclude. The detainment or aliening of things by Law conſecrated to ſupport pure worſhip of the true God without ſuperfluitie, any longer then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie requires, is Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>Tythes haue beene by Law conſecrated to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of pure worſhip of the true God, are not ſuperfluous, and now no neceſſitie of their alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Ergo,</hi> their detainement is Sacriledge.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="letter">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:133:39"/>
                        <head>REVERENDO IN CHRISTO PATRI, AC DOMINO, GEORGIO PROVIDENTIA DIVINA EPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopo CICESTRENSI obſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam plurimam.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorande Praeſul, Gratulor, ſanè gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulor mihimet ipſe hanc qualemcunque gratiſsimi erga te animi mei testandi <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Adverſarium nacti ſumus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacem, mordicacem plus ſatis, inſulſum tamen. Eum ego ſalibus, opinor, meis ſatis ſuperque conditum ad te mitto. Sale (videſis) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te an tuo condiendum. Déprecor. Quorſum enim? Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, faetet, neſcio quo modo, apud vulgus noſtrum, ſiquid fortè aſperius in istiuſmodi faetulentias animadverta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: et dulcius reſipit, vt Dario in fuga, quicquid tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baverit in foetore diſciplina ſanior. Fruantur, per me licet, putore ſuo: Tantùm ne me, ne meos in volutabrum pertentent ſuum.</p>
                        <p>Ieiuni quicquid id eſt in hac Apologia nostra, tenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati, obſecro, condones meae. Robusti ſiquid et ſolidi, hoc ego propè totum tibi acceptum fero. Aut fama mendax,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:133:40"/> aut tu aliquando meam Oxonij excuſam de iure Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum velitationem legisti, calculo tuo approbasti. Mendax ſim, niſi <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, vt ſunt, tua dialecticam adhuc et nutantem ſententiam meam aſpectu primo fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maverint, atque in ſolidum fundaverint. Inibi ſum, et fixus haereo. Ignoſcas, quaeſo, valetudinario, et quamvis paulo plus quadragenario, ſenectute tamen (proh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um) praematura, et Calculo Renum praegravido, grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinoſo, ſi non equo aut pedibus ad te viſendum, conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum festinaverim. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, vt ego eruditionem, modeſtiam, dignitatem tuam exoſculor, et planè vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Deus Opt. Max. Amplitudinem tuam incolumem ſer vet, vt, quod ſtrenuè adhuc fecisti, Decimas Eccleſiae aſſeras, vindices; Decumanum hunc fluctum planè Naufragum ab Eccleſia propulſes; Clerum tuum ab eo protegas. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Amplitudinis tuae perquam ſtudioſus GVILIELMVS SCLATER.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:133:40"/>
            <p>TO this Argument made longſome by idle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, thus my Brother Clerique. <hi>All may here be granted alſo without danger. For no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that things conſecrated in the new Teſtament, is the portion by the word of God allotted to Miniſters: nor that the detainement or alienation thereof is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: nor that (as the ſtate of the Church now ſtands with vs) Tythes are that portion; and ſo that Tythes are allotted by the word of God for our maintenance euen vnder the new Teſtament. But the quaeſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any portion whatſoeuer once conſecrated be perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and onely due in all Ages; And ſo whether Tythes be that onely and perpetuall portion for euer; which by this Argument is not prooued. For howſoeuer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement and alienation of Tythes bee Sacriledge (as things now ſtand with vs) yet the change of Tythes into another kinde of maintenance as good or better, is no Sacriledge. For that which</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Carleton <hi>ſaith to the contrarie, fol.</hi> 26. <hi>is of no force. For first there is a great difference betweene things conſecrated to the vſe of Gods worſhip in the Temple vnder the old Testament (of which ſort the veſſels were whereof he ſpeaketh) and things dedicated to the Churches and Ministers vſe in the New. For thoſe were Types and Sacraments of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things (as appeareth by thoſe very veſſels, by</hi> 2. Tim. 2.20, 21.) <hi>but ſo are not theſe. Secondly, Tythes euen in the old Teſtament might be changed, ſo long as no detriment came therby to the Leuites,</hi> Leu. 27.31. <hi>So that though it were granted that Tythes were due</hi> iure diuino <hi>(which he takes for granted ſophiſtically) yet by
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133:41"/> his owne reaſon they may be changed, becauſe the change is allowed by the ſame power and Authoritie by which they are made holy to God. Thirdly, he playes the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister manifestly in arguing</hi> a dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter; <hi>for thus he reaſoneth: It is Sacriledge to change Tythes for a maintenance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of leſſe value then Tythes: Ergo, it is ſimply Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge to make an exchange of them: which whether it be a good forme of Reaſoning, I leaue to others to iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> My liberall Aduerſarie, how ſhall I praiſe your bountie? What tearmes may I deuiſe to commend it? Certeinly, but that I know there be many, for all your ſaying, who deny my praemiſes, I ſhould thinke you and all men conſenting to the concluſion; which you may, without new quaeſtion, aſſure your ſelfe to be meant of a perpetuall and vnalterable por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen therefore, becauſe conſecrated.</p>
            <p>But whereto I wonder all this ſhew of granting all, except to ſhow your ſelfe wittie? Why ſuch circling? why ſpeake you not in the tearmes of your Maſter that Heretique in Philoſophy, and ſay any propoſition is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As once a <hi>Rabbi</hi> in that haereſie, and other ſchiſme beeing demaunded what he thought of the Sermon he ſate to cenſure, ſaid; the man and his matter and gifts he well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued; onely one doctrine was not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thus take my anſwer to your quaeſtion; Nothing ſanctified may euer be commoned, except by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of that God to whom they are ſanctified. Whether changed with your limits, is a quaeſtion coincident, whereof anone.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:133:41"/>
            <p>Of things conſecrated are two ſorts; ſome which God; ſome which man ſanctifieth: of Gods ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, you haue inſtances many in old Teſtament; of Time the ſeuenth; of ſubſtance, once we are ſure, the tenth. And of this kinde, but you, now perhaps, none quaeſtions, whether any may be vnhallowed without warrant from the Sanctifier.</p>
            <p>Is the quaeſtion of that which man ſanctifieth; whether euer by mans owne Authoritie it may war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably be vnhallowed? thus is the anſwer diſtinct, as ſuddenneſſe permits it to be propounded: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Gods act and mans in ſanctifying paſſeth on the ſame matter; <hi>God ſanctified the Sabbath,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 2.3.</note> by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to his owne vſe; yet we reade in <hi>Iſay</hi> after ſome tranſlations, <hi>If</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 58.13.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt call it a delight to conſecrate it as Glorious vnto the Lord. The</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>temple of God is holy which yee are;</hi> our bodies and ſoules are Gods; yet ſaid <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>offer vp your ſelues vnto God.</hi> Such votarie conſecration by man of things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready holy to God, multiplies the obligations to render; aggrauates malice of Sacriledge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes man conſecrates what God hath left common, as <hi>Ananias the price of his poſſeſsions:</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 5.2.</note> whether dominion or vſe, as Canoniſts diſtinguiſh, ioyntly or ſeuerally, it matters not here to ſpecifie: of this kinde of things ſanctified is all the quaeſtion. For my part I doubt not but the character of Gods firſt impreſſion in Tythes, is indeleble; and that mans votarie conſecration of them, gaue them no new hallowing, but encreaſed obligation to their payment. Howbeit <hi>ex abundante,</hi> I will ſuppoſe they haue no other touch of holines, then mans deuotion hath put to them.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:133:42"/>
            <p>Thus is the Argument for the maine vpon that ſuppoſall. <hi>Its</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Prou. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>a curſe to deuoure that which is ſanctified;</hi> that is, any thing that is ſanctified, at any time. <hi>And after the vow to inquire;</hi> this laſt clauſe forceth to iudge, he meanes of things votarily, or voluntarily conſecrated by man. Will you ſay, <hi>while its ſanctified;</hi> or as the <hi>caſe ſtands with them amongst whom its ſanctified?</hi> You call to minde the idle euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Arminians in the quaeſtion of Apoſtaſie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be incident to men regenerate. We ſay as S. <hi>Iohn;</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>He thats borne of God ſinnes not</hi> the ſinne vnto death: True, ſay they, <hi>quàtalis,</hi> or <hi>quandiu ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi> Whereas euery man knowes that Apoſtaſie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not from regeneration; and that it implies a ceaſing to bee <hi>talis;</hi> and therefore neceſſarily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the <hi>quandiu talis.</hi> Euery man knowes, a ſober man is not drunke as he is a ſober man, or ſo long as he is ſober; drunkenneſſe proceedes not from ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie; and it implies, to ſay, <hi>ebrius, quandiu ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once ſanctified, euer ſanctified; if th'intendement of the votarie were for perpetuitie. I haue heard of the rule, <hi>Eius est tollere; cuius ponere;</hi> but I aske your iudgement, whether<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 5.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ananias</hi> his reuocation of part vpon ſecond thoughts, did excuſe him of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides there is by ſuch vow or deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, a new propertie and dominion giuen vnto God in the thing deuoted. Shall man, can man defeate God of that propertie? <hi>dic ſodes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the quaeſtion now of the change? Whether the ſanctified portion may be changed, and another with
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133:42"/> your cautions ſubſtituted in ſtead thereof? I ſhould thinke not. Eſpecially if you meane as you muſt, a change of the whole kinde, for perpetuitie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that God allowed no change of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; Much leſſe of the whole kinde. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 27.33. <hi>He ſhall not looke vpon it whether it be good or bad,</hi> but the Tenth muſt be rendred in the particular; becauſe thats it that is holy to the Lord, ſaid hee, euer the tenth or the aequiualent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, <hi>Salomon; Say not before th'Angel</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Eccl. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>it was an errour,</hi> I was miſtaken in the matter vowed; take another which vpon ſecond thoughts is found better. Why ſhould the Lord deſtroy thee not in thy time?</p>
            <p n="3">3. I finde the command peremptorie and prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe <hi>to pay that which is vowed,</hi> that is, as I take it, that very particular.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe I obſerue paenaltie (as I conceiue) infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in caſe of exchange attempted;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Leuit. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and the change must be the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Vpon grant of power to exchange, the matter of Sacriledge muſt bee vncertaine, and no man chargeable with that ſinne as vpon certeintie.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Why not diminution of part as free from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, as exchange? which yet in <hi>Ananias</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 5.</note> his caſe is damned.</p>
            <p>But is it naught to purpoſe which the now reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop of <hi>Chichester</hi> ſaid to this point of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change? heare him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Sacriledge be in taking away holy things from God and his Church, it appeareth more in taking away Tythes then in any other thing whatſoeuer. Neither can
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133:43"/> Sacriledge herein be excuſed, though men ſhould eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh ſomething in place of that holy thing taken away?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe the changing of holy things is Sacriledge no leſſe (though haply a leſſe kinde of Sacriledge) then taking away of the ſame. If</hi> Nabuchadnezzar <hi>hauing taken away th'holy veſſels out of the houſe of the Lord, ſhould in place thereof haue put ſome other, might his Sacriledge thereby be excuſed? or</hi> Beltazzar <hi>taking the veſſels of the Lords houſe, and in them banquetting with his Lords and Concubines, if he ſhould in ſtead thereof haue placed other, could any iustifie his Sacriledge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? no more can the taking away of Tythes be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though ſomething in place thereof ſhould be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His opinion you are not bound to ſubſcribe vnto; perhaps he is not yet growne claſſicall: but what to his Reaſon? For things which God himſelfe hath ſanctified?</p>
            <p>Forſooth; <hi>This difference there is betwixt things conſecrated to the vſe of Gods worſhip in the Temple vnder the old Teſtament (of which ſort the veſſels were whereof he ſpeakes) and of things dedicated to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Miniſters vſe in the new: for thoſe were Types and Sacraments of other things (as appeares of thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry veſſels, by</hi> 2. Tim. 2.20, 21.) <hi>ſo not theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Right ſo. Yet when I from ground as good or better affirme firſt fruits myſticall reſemblances of Chriſt and the gifts of the Spirit in this life giuen, how merily game you at mee?</p>
            <p>But ſay in good ſadneſſe: is there in <hi>this point of vnalterableneſſe without diuine Authoritie</hi> a diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwixt things then conſecrated by God in Old
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:133:43"/> Teſtament, and thoſe by him hallowed in New? or hath God giuen more libertie of exchanging things ſanctified in New, then of thoſe other hallowed in Old Teſtament? What one paſſage of Scripture haue you to guide you? Belongs not this to both Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? <hi>Its</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Prou. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>a curſe to deuoure holy things.</hi> And, <hi>thou that abhorreſt Idols,</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>committest thou Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge?</hi> put differences, as many as you will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt one and other in other reſpects, in this of <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſſe</hi> whereof is quaeſtion, you ſhall neuer be able to cut difference.</p>
            <p>This it ſeemes you ſaw well enough, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your <hi>ſecondarily</hi> auoucheth with too much confidence, that<note n="x" place="margin">Leu. 27.31.</note> 
               <hi>Tythes might then be changed ſo long as no detriment came by th'exchange to Leuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Belike then your difference is not vniuerſall for things conſecrated in Old Teſtament; for ſome of them might be changed, as you doe handſomely inſtance <hi>in propoſito,</hi> the point quaeſtioned of Tythes. Phi, phi; why dye you changeable? might they not be changed, and yet might they be changed? <hi>Pugnantia loqui te non vides?</hi> Or if you meant your vnchangeableneſſe particularly to the veſſels of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the Temple, could no other particular of things then conſecrated alterably be inſtanced in, but the Tythes in quaeſtion? Why haue you ſo forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten notorious abſurdities in diſputation?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But thinke you indeede Tythes might then be changed in that ſort which now we quaeſtion? Might Iſraelites haue changed that kinde of maintaining Leuites by Tythes, into another as good or better? Say I beſeech you. Or had it not beene profane
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133:44"/> arrogancie in that people to haue altered Gods prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript for the manner of maintenance, vnder prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of bettering it?</p>
            <p>Will your text prooue it? It ſpeakes indeede of<note n="y" place="margin">Leuit. 27.31.</note> 
               <hi>redeeming a particular Tythe;</hi> not a ſyllable of <hi>changing the</hi> whole kinde of maintenance into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for perpetuitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe you Redemption euen of a particular <hi>approoued?</hi> or rather <hi>tolerated?</hi> Tolerated I ſhould thinke; and not allowed. Becauſe <hi>mulcted with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a fift part.</hi> That, in caſe a man were ſo head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong in his affection that he would needs redeeme, way ſhould be giuen: Howbeit, by his paenaltie he muſt be taught that in the act and attempt he erred. My inducement is this: Becauſe I euer obſerue addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a fift part ordered to be made ouer and aboue the ſatisfaction or amends for the treſpaſſe or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, how elſe, but <hi>nomine poenae.</hi> Compare theſe Scriptures, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 5.15. and 6.5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.6, 7. <hi>Et ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi.</hi> And aptly, it tended not to praeuent dammage of Leuites, which eaſily enough was, or might be prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented in the price giuen for ranſome.</p>
            <p>But how glad am I to ſee you carefull to praeuent dammage of Leuites in the exchange? and ſo cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate for Miniſters indemnitie? In caſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of Tythes into another kinde of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, you cautionately prouide, it muſt bee <hi>as good or better.</hi> Et mox, <hi>exchange is no robberie in this kinde, prouided alwaies that it be made, in an aequall proportion at the least, ſo as if the Church be not bettered, yet it is not damnified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſing on your heart for that yet, If euer Lay-Parſon,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133:44"/> or ſcrupulous Gentleman, or Cuſtomarie Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner cun you thanke for your refutation, I much maruell. Say, I pray you, doth the ſcrupulous Gentleman ſo prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe? Giues hee the aequiualent to the Tythe? If I knew him, and he ſo practiſe, at firſt greeting I would ciuilly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him. Miracle, mirror at leaſt he ſhould be to me, of all the Lay-Order of Parſons, whom I yet know. I may tranſgreſſe Charitie in my iealouſie of that blacke Swan. But how feare I? leaſt the little grumble of Conſcience be calmed with that parcell of your opinion, <hi>Tythes may be changed into another kind of maintenance,</hi> and no care taken of your Prouiſo, for <hi>ſubſtitution of an aequiualent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once I know tenne or twentie pounds Coyne-ſtipend is no aequall proportion to an hundred or two, or three, in Tythes; nor two-pence Rate or Cuſtome aequiualent to ten or twentie ſhillings of Tithes. Thinke of it my Maſter Parſons of the Laitie; your beſt Patron ſteedes you not, as you practiſe. But I returne to the Refuter.</p>
            <p>What ſay you to that of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Carleton? When any thing conſecrated is taken away, that a thing of the ſame value ſhould be reſtored,</hi> who can expect? and who ſhal be Iudge?</p>
            <p>Forſooth, he <hi>playeth the Sophister manifestly, in arguing</hi> à dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpliciter; <hi>for thus he reaſoneth: Its Sacriledge to change Tythes for a maintenance and prouiſion of leſſe value then Tythes.</hi> Ergo, <hi>its ſimply Sacriledge, to make exchange of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But doth he ſo reaſon indeede? you would make him a ſimple Sophiſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus rather conceiue him; to apprehend that ſuppoſed (ſomething) to bee ſubſtituted in roome of Tythes, of ambiguous acception: there is <hi>aliquid indefini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> where ſomething, is any thing: And there is <hi>hoc ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid,</hi> or <hi>aliquid limitatum,</hi> as in this caſe ſufficient prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or in your meaning, ſomething aequiualent.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:133:45"/>
            <p>Is the ſomething to be ſubſtituted, indefinite? any ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in lieu of Tythes? that reſtitution or ſubſtitution, according to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Carleton,</hi> and according to cleare eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Truth, cannot be excuſed of Sacriledge; for it may be of leſſe value, its likely to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Is it, <hi>hoc aliquid; aliquid limitatum;</hi> after the opinion there mentioned, a ſufficient prouiſion? that is a Caſtle in the ayre, as he there truly ſpeakes; beſides, not that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient maintenance which God hath allotted; and in all likelyhood, not ſo ſufficient: by conſequent therefore ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiouſly ſubſtituted.</p>
            <p>Is it your aequiualent? as good or better? To this, thus he truly; <hi>None can name any ſo conuenient as Tythes, to ſupply the place of Tythes; ſo as to be ſufficient at all times, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the price of things riſe or fall. Which proportioning of the Miniſters eſtate, making it able to anſwer all eſtates alike, whether deare or cheape, proceeding from the wiſedome of God, cannot be matched by mans wiſedome.</hi> Thus take him in forme.</p>
            <p>Euery change of Tythes into another kind of prouiſion, which is at any time of leſſe worth or conueniencie then Tythes, is ſacrilegious. But all exchange of Tythes into any other kind of prouiſion, is at ſome time neceſſarily of leſſe worth &amp; conueniencie then Tythes. <hi>Ergo,</hi> all change of Tithes into any other kind of prouiſion, is ſacrilegious. Of the <hi>Maior,</hi> your limits in exchanging, permit not you to doubt. The <hi>Minor</hi> is thus proued. No other prouiſion can make the Miniſters eſtate able at all times to anſwer all eſtates. <hi>Ergo,</hi> euery exchange of Tythes into another prouiſion is, <hi>vt ſupra,</hi> of leſſe worth and conueniencie. What thinke you? did the Doctor reaſon <hi>a dicto ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter?</hi> did not the Batchelor ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther view him <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> and not <hi>ſimpliciter?</hi> I ſhould thinke this rather.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:133:45"/>
            <p>As to what you talke of Canoniſts opinion, and Miniſters practiſe in commutation or compoſition for Tythes, it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not the purpoſe: let all be granted lawfull; what is this to a change of Tythes for perpetuitie?</p>
            <p>Remember you not your owne Dunſe Canoniſt, reſoluing that Tythes cannot be granted to a Laicke in fee? haue you forgotten, that in quaeſtion of ſelling particular Tythes, they diſtinguiſh betwixt things Tythable, and the <hi>ius</hi> of Tything? Sale of <hi>res decimabilis,</hi> they allow with cautions: marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing the <hi>ius</hi> of Tything, they make Simoniacall and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious. Their reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Ius decimandi</hi> is <hi>ſpirituali officio annexum.</hi> And in caſe ſuch a permutation of Tythes as you ſpeake of, were lawfull, why not alſo a transferring of the <hi>ius</hi> of Tything?</p>
            <p>To cloſe this point, I muſt profeſſe, I like not ſuch permu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or compoſitions for Tythes, except in way of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, where ſcandall is feared. It hath brought vpon the Church, Cuſtomes and Preſcriptions, ſo many, of ſo long continuance, that of Tythe, except the name of Tythe, is left almoſt nothing to many Churches.</p>
            <p>I profeſſe not Canoniſt: yet thus much I know; Miniſters haue no perfect dominion in Tythes, or other endowments of the Church; &amp; am inclined to thinke, they are at moſt but vſe-fructuaries therein. The whole right &amp; diſpoſe of Tythes is not in Miniſters, no nor in the Church <hi>fundamentaliter or terminativè:</hi> firſt and originally<note n="z" place="margin">Leu. 27. Mal. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>they are Gods;</hi> by him as chief proprietary aſſigned to the Prieſthood, for preſeruation of their office, &amp; ſupport of the ſeruice by them adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>The fourth Reaſon followeth: The Law firſt allotting Tythes, to ſupport of the Miniſterie, and worſhip of God, was morall; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are perpetually the Miniſters Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That Law conceiue to be that which guided <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> in the practiſe of Tything: reuiued afterwards, and further explained, what time they were aſſigned to <hi>Leui.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:133:46"/>
            <p>That it was morall, perpetually binding, is thus euident; becauſe in no reſpect caeremoniall, or particularly iudiciall to the ſtate of Iewes: you vnderſtand, I preſume, by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument thus moulded, that we meane it meerely morall.</p>
            <p>Rather ſaith my learned friend; <hi>mixti iuris; In diuerſe reſpects, Tythes are both morall, and caeremoniall, and iudiciall; as was alſo the Sabbath in the old Testament. They are morall, as a ſufficient maintenance for Ministers of holy things. Caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, as Rites of the Iewiſh Religion: Iudicial, as maintenance of Leuites and Leuiticall Priests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So as you ſay; and not without conſent and ſuffrage of ſome both old Schoole-men, and moderne more Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe Teachers. There are Lawes and duties of mixt nature; as long before M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iunius</hi> taught more then one introducto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie teacher of Schoole-diuinitie.<note place="margin">Amandus de bello viſu, &amp;c.</note> But, I pray you, by Tythes meane you the <hi>quota?</hi> and ſay you, in that very quantity they are morally belonging to Miniſters of holy things? Sir, <hi>wee are brethren, why ſtriue we?</hi> you grant the quaeſtion. Let them be in what other reſpects you wil, caeremonious, or iudiciall, or both; if in that <hi>quota</hi> they are morally due, I ſhal be ready to ſwear anon, they are perpetually due to Miniſters of holy things. And me thinkes by your example of the Sabbath, which you giue for inſtance of the like, you ſhould meane ſo. For that, I preſume, you grant euen in the quotient of Time-morall: though there were ſome acceſſories of Caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monialitie and iudicialitie alſo perhaps annexed thereto. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the very Name of Tythes determinately denotes that certaine Portion; the Tenth part of Temporall ſubſtance. So that in ſaying Tythes are morall, though with a <hi>Quatenus,</hi> you ſay as much as, the tenth part of the peoples Income by Law moral belongs to Miniſters of holy things. Or elſe giue vs, I pray you, th'other part of your diſtinction, or ſome other reſpect in which they are not moral. They are moral as a <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient maintenance;</hi> not moral belike; as <hi>an inſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:133:46"/> As if I ſhould ſay; The ſeauenth of time is morally preſcribed, as it is a ſufficient time to bee ſpent in the ſeruice of God: not morally, as inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Whereas to ſay Truth, Gods determining this numerall certeintie of Time and Subſtance to his ſeruice, noticeth it as that ſufficiency which we muſt reſt in.</p>
            <p>And yet meethinkes you ſhould not meane ſo as your words purport. For then, why ſtriue you for lawfulneſſe of mans exchanging that maintenance into another kinde of prouiſion as good or better. Surely vpon ſuppoſall of that meaning, were I a man transported with paſſion, I ſhould bee ready to cry out as you; <hi>Oh horrible, Is it poſsible a Minister of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſhould teach that man may alter or reuerſe Gods morall praecepts? And if an Angell from heauen ſhould ſay ſo, I know how to esteeme him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how handſomely might a man with ſuch a <hi>quatenus,</hi> maintaine ſacrifices and burnt offerings to be morall; yea and the duty whatſoeuer it is, that is moſt meerely morall, to bee caeremoniall and Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all? The<note n="a" place="margin">Ioſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Sacrifices of the Lord God of Iſrael made by fire was Leuies inheritance;</hi> part of his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; impleade me, if you liſt, for ſaying they are morall; vrge as you well may, that they were meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caeremoniall; my diſtinction is ready; in diuers reſpects they are caeremoniall, and Iudiciall and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Caeremoniall as rites of the Iewiſh religion; Iudiciall as <hi>Leuies</hi> inheritance; yet morall as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency, and part of ſufficient maintenance aſſigned to Miniſters of holy things. And could I not ſhift, trow you, to maintaine prayer Ceremoniall, or Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:133:47"/> Preſſe mee with your greateſt inſtance to prooue it morall; twentie to one but I ſhall finde a <hi>quatenus,</hi> that hath vnder it as much truth, as yours in the caſe of Tythes; though as ſpirituall worſhip, its morall; yet as part of Tabernacle and Temple ſeruice, ſo its caeremoniall; as a meane to obtaine and praeſerue our ſuſtenance and temporalities; ſo its Iudiciall. So be it if you will haue it ſo.</p>
            <p>But ſay for Gods ſake, and vexe vs no more with impertinent manners of ſpeech. By Tythes the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in this propoſition, <hi>Tythes are morall, quatenus, &amp;c.</hi> Meane you the tenth part of temporalities? Then Tythes are morall, and we haue the purpoſe; And muſt you not ſo meane it, as in th'other, Tythes, that is, tenth part are caeremoniall; and Tenthes are Iudiciall. Let the tenth parts be caeremoniall or iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall with what <hi>quatenus</hi> they will, if they bee caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall or iudiciall with a <hi>quatenus,</hi> then <hi>eatenus</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tenthes are caeremoniall or iudiciall; So let Tenthes be morall with a <hi>quatenus,</hi> yet <hi>eatenus</hi> the Tenth part of peoples Temporalties by morall law belongs to Miniſters of holy things. Briefly, meane you by Tythes, <hi>Decimam partem temporalis ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> in all three members; or meane you it in the two latter propoſitions, not in the firſt? If you meane it, Tythes are morall; if you ſo meane not, you play the abſurd ſophiſter, the idle diſputant in taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or altering <hi>ſubiectum quaestionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceede to euidence the firſt member of th' Antecedent. That the law inioyning Tyths was in no reſpect caeremoniall. Caeremoniall ordinances were all <hi>ſhadowes of things to come,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Col. 2.17</note> 
               <hi>the body whereof is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:133:47"/> Chriſt.</hi> This no ſuch ſhadow, for where is the body which this ſuppoſed caeremonies dutie ſhould ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow? Some haue ſheaped vs this reſemblance. The number of Tenne is a number of perfection, and by paying in this number, the offerer made proteſtation of his owne imperfection, and of his expecting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Chriſt. Pretty too too. Twenty ſuch like a tolerable wit would deuiſe. But can they ſhew vs this ſignification or end of payment in Scripture, but obſcurely ſo much as by alluſion intimated? I dare ſay no; nor any other end, no not of their payment to <hi>Leui:</hi> but ſupport of Gods worſhip and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Leuiticall caeremonies haue all analogicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the things they praefigured: Therefore called <hi>ſhadowes of things to come.</hi> Becauſe as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy carries a darke, yet ſome reſemblance of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whoſe ſhadow it is; ſo caeremonies of Chriſt and his benefits, &amp;c. Therefore alſo tearmed<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 9.23</note> 
               <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of heauenly things,</hi> being ordained by their very ſemblance to<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>teach the rude.</hi> Tything hath no analogicall reſemblance of imperfection, or thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, or Gods vniuerſall dominion: for who can, I ſay not only avow his frame, but frame it except abſurdly? Giue vs ſuch analogie of this, as we are able to ſhow of others, we will then beleeue their payment to haue beene in part, at leaſt, Leuitically caeremonious. Of ſprinklings and purifyings, of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, of Arke, of high Prieſt (and indeede of what not? that was truly a ſhadow of heauenly things) we finde analogie in the word of God. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 9.7.12.</note> 
               <hi>As high Priest amongst Iewes alone entered into the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:133:48"/> holy of holies not without blood: So Christ into heauen:</hi> &amp;c. Can thoſe who ſo confidently avow tything a caeremonie, thus draw out the ſimilitude twixt it and heauenly things?</p>
            <p n="3">3. No Leuiticall caeremonie may be vſed after full publiſhing of the Goſpel; Schoolemen ſay well, <hi>Iudicialia post Chriſtum</hi> bee <hi>mortua,</hi> becauſe they binde not: <hi>Caeremonialia mortifera;</hi> their very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuing is vnlawfull and deadly. But payment of Tythes by conſent of all, except Browniſts, may be retained. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I finde not that the Lord in Propheticall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures taxeth ſo much th'omiſſion of caeremonies, or exacteth in ſo ſtrict termes their performance, as hee doth this of Tythes. Something I finde of their faultie performance, ſomething of their ſticking in them with neglect of moralities: And this to mee is a praeſumption, they were other then caeremonies.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I neuer read Chriſt ſpeake ſo much of any Iewiſh Caeremonie, as he did of Tythes;<note n="f" place="margin">Math. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things ought yee not to leaue vndone;</hi> though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as much might haue beene ſaid of Caeremonies during thoſe times. All theſe conſidered, may I not conclude of Tything, it was no Leuiticall caere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie?</p>
            <p>To theſe Arguments thus hath my friend. <hi>That all Caeremonies were ſhadowes of things to come, I would not haue ſuppoſed you would haue held; but that I ſee it in Print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you may chooſe yet whether you will thinke it or no if you take my exegeticall termes of limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For I meane of Caeremonies, Leuiticall,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:133:48"/> Moſaicall, Aaronicall Caeremonies; as wee vſe to take them contradiſtinctly to moralities and Iewiſh iudicials. And ſo vnderſtanding mee, why would you not thinke it? I aſſure you I ſhame not to haue it in Print.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For all men know that there are two ſorts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Caeremonies in all Religions whatſoeuer: ſome ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant and Sacramentall and Myſticall, other ſome for decencie and good order, And if Tythes be ſaid to bee Caeremonies of order, I know no exception can be taken againſt it.</hi> 2. <hi>But we may goe one degree farther and ſay with</hi> Iunius, <hi>that of ſignificant or myſticall caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies there are three ſorts; one remembrances of things past; another demonſtrations of things praeſent: a third figures or ſhadowes of things to come: or as</hi> Beza <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Signa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Sabbath may ſerue for an example in all theſe reſpects, and whether Tythes were ſo or no who can tell? This we neede not be afraid to ſay, that Tythes were remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of benefits receiued in times past, and demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a thankefull minde for the time praeſent. For ſo they were in</hi> Abraham, Gen. 14.20. <hi>And</hi> Iacob <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.22. <hi>Yea in the whole time of th'Old Testament, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were an oblation to the Lord, Numb.</hi> 18.24, 26, 27, 28. <hi>And for my part alſo I am halfe perſwaded that they were ſhadowes of things to come: If you aske mee where is the bodie which they ſhadowed? I dare not tell you my minde, leaſt you laugh mee out of Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſay its the deuiſe of a tolerable wit. This therefore is that which I ſay, that ſeeing the bodies of all caeremoniall ſhadowes are not made knowne vnto vs, it may as well be ſo for any thing yet appeareth, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:133:49"/> And if it be not ſo in Tythes, yet if they be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant in the two former reſpects, yea if they were not ſignificant at all, but only inſtituted for good order, it is ſufficient to diſprooue that aſſertion, that all Caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were ſhadowes of things to come. Yea it is ſufficient alſo to anſwer your ſecond reaſon, Caeremonies haue an analogicall reſemblance of the things they ſignified: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this praeſumeth the former to be true, that Caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are ſhadowes of things to come: yea and the third too, for that hereby it appeareth, that that may be a cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie, which was before the Law not foreſhadowing Christ. And whereas you ſay, No Leuiticall caeremonie may be vſed after publiſhing of the Goſpel; and alleadge thereto the ſaying of the Schoolemen, Iudicialia post Christum mortua ſunt; Caeremonialia verò mortifera,</hi> Iunius <hi>ſeemes to mee to vnderſtand it better of Caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſhadowes onely, and of Caeremonies Leuiticall ſo farre forth onely as any of them doth ſhadow ſomething in Christ: granting that though in other reſpects they be in their owne Nature mutable, yet that there is no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſsitie of remoouall thereof. So that you ſee, that though it were granted that Tythes were ſhadowes of things to come, yet they may be retained, ſo long as they are not retained in that regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this anſwereth to the full, all that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Carleton <hi>alleadgeth to this purpoſe, Page</hi> 16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Whether in iest or good earnest. For he alſo praeſuppoſeth all Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies to be ſhadowes of things to come. Where by the way it is good ſport to ſee what game he maketh of this: that we ſay, Tythes are now vſed in the time of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel not as a Caeremonie but as another thing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon rideth the hackney diſtinction of Materialiter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:133:49"/> verum est, ſed non formaliter, out of breath; to which neuertheleſſe he must be beholden in the end whether he will or no. For fol.</hi> 35. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>When he anſwereth</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulenſis, <hi>that Tythes haue two reſpects; one in their generall ordinance, another in their particular aſsigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and in regard of the former not inſtituted by the Law, but onely in the latter; what is this (I would faine know) but non materialiter, ſed formaliter?</hi> &amp;c. The reſt my loue couers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer. I hope you thinke nor D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Carleton</hi> nor poore mee ſo ſimple or vnskilled, as not to know the notation of the name (whether of <hi>Cares</hi> the Tuſcane towne, or a <hi>carendo</hi>) and the generall notion of the Nature of Caeremonies. Well we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it generally to denote any externall rite of religion. This alſo wee conceiue, that there were Caeremonies in this generall ſenſe taken, in vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Iewes, which ſort ſufficiently with the ſtate of the Goſpel. There are naturall Caeremonies, ſuch as lifting vp of hands and eyes to heauen, bowing the knee, proſtrating the bodie in prayer: Religious rites apparently Naturall, and by Natures inſtinct in vſe amongſt Gentiles as well as Iewes. Neither much contend we, but there were ſome externall rites of Gods inſtitution for Iewes which yet are applicable to Euangelicall worſhip.</p>
            <p>But when we treat of Caeremonies contradiſtinct to moralities we meane and explicate our ſelues of caeremonies <hi>Leuiticall, Moſaicall,</hi> or if you pleaſe ſo to terme them, <hi>Aaronicall</hi> Caeremonies. Whoſe ſtile in <hi>Paul</hi> is vniuerſally, <hi>elements, beggarly elements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauenly things of things, to come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4 9.</note> 
               <hi>The law
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:133:50"/> whereof</hi> was reſpectiue onely of the <hi>Leuiticall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And of theſe this is that we teach; 1. That they were <hi>all figures of things to come. Similitudes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things; ſhadowes of Christ</hi> and ſpirituall things then promiſed, now exhibited.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of theſe we haue further learnd; 1. That they retained their vertue and power of binding till the death of Chriſt. 2. That they were after his death, for a time, <hi>liberae obſeruationis,</hi> for more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable bringing of the Synagogue to the graue; as not the now reuerend Biſhop of Chicheſter, but that old renowmed of <hi>Hippo</hi> firſt ſpake. Were alſo for that time to be tempered in vſe by rules of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, in fauour of weake Iewes, till fuller preaching of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yet were after promulgation of the Goſpell <hi>mortiferae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. 2. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 102. <hi>Art.</hi> 4.</note> and could not, as <hi>Thomas</hi> ſpeakes, be vſed <hi>ſine mortali peccato.</hi> Will you heare his reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their vſe implyed proteſtation of ſuch faith, as who ſhall now in dayes of new Teſtament pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, were worthy to be branded with note of groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt haereſie, no leſſe then Iudaiſme. The faith of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before Chriſt, and ours ſince him, is in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one; yet were th'Articles thereof to be ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in termes different. Theirs, as denoting Chriſt then to come; ours, as importing Chriſt already come. Proportionally their caeremonies were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſignifie things to come; and vſe thereof implyed ſuch proteſtation in that people. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould ſinne mortally, whoſoeuer ſhould now in profeſſion of his faith <hi>by words,</hi> ſay, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:133:50"/> in Chriſt, yet to be borne, to die, to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: ſo no leſſe mortally he, who ſhall vſe any <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all protestation or profeſsion in fact</hi> of ſuch faith, as who ſo vſeth theſe caeremonies, neceſſarily muſt doe, <hi>I am non promittitur naſciturus, paſſurus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin. Cont. Fauſt. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. lib. <hi>19.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>reſurrectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, quod illa Sacramenta quodammodo perſonabant: ſed annunciatur quod natus ſit, &amp; reſurrexit, quod haec Sacramenta quae a Christianis aguntur iam perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What trow you? Will our Arguments now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede? Caeremonious ordinances Leuiticall were all ſhadowes of things to come, carrying analogicall reſemblance of what they ſignified, &amp;c. <hi>Videſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Not ſo; for euery man knowes all Religions haue ſome caeremonies of order and decency; not all ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and myſticall; And ſo might Tythes be caeremonies of order, ſay alſo of decency if you pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely, I doubt not but the whole Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſeruice of God was carried in the ſeemelieſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and that there was ſtrict obſeruation of <hi>prius</hi> and <hi>posterius</hi> in all their <hi>Cultus.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> 
               <hi>Let all things bee done decently and in order,</hi> is a rule of the Law of Nature, and bound Iewes as well as Chriſtians. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make I quaeſtion but Iewes had directions euen for the order and outward faſhion of their caeremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious ſeruice, of Gods owne praeſcript, that the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> might be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But Sir you muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1. That in the quaeſtion of Tythes, and the like, whether they were Leuiticall Ceremonies or no, we inquire of the Materials of Leuiticall ſeruice; and not of the <hi>modus</hi> and externe faſhion of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, which commonly comes vnder the terme
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:133:51"/> of decency and order. 2. Next, I dare you to inſtance in but one caeremonie of order, if it were properlie Leuiticall, vpon condition to looſe the benefite of this Argument if I euidence not, that it was of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſignification; and Typicall of ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Chriſt or his kingdome. Be it then that they had their caeremonies of order, yet if thoſe alſo were ſhadowy and figurall, how helpes your diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to contradict our propoſition?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet <hi>one ſtep further you will aduenture</hi> to goe; and its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I warrant you. <hi>Not all ſhadowes of things to come; for ſome were remembrances of things paſt; ſome demonſtration of things praeſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Scot. in <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Euen ſo; wee haue long ſince learned of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iunius</hi> his Maſters, that ſignes are ſome Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue, ſome demonſtratiue, ſome prognoſticall. But can you name vs the Leuiticall caeremonie, that was ſo commemoratiue of things paſt, or demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of things praeſent, that it was not alſo Typical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prognoſticall of things to come? I dare not bee ouer confident; memory decaies as age growes, and I am ſuddenned to addreſſe this anſwer to you. But cannot bethinke my ſelfe, nor I (ſuppoſe) you, of any Leuiticall Caeremonie, whether <hi>ſacrum</hi> or <hi>ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>ſacramentum,</hi> or <hi>obſervantia,</hi> but was withall ſhadow of ſomething to come. The paſſeouer, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of <hi>Angels paſsing ouer Iſraelites,</hi> yet withall <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Type of Chriſt:</hi> The Manna reſerued in the Arke, <hi>monument of the</hi> materiall <hi>bread</hi> miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly giuen <hi>from heauen;</hi> but was it not alſo Type of Chriſt, the<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> 
               <hi>liuing bread which came downe from heauen?</hi> That ſpight of the pie it muſt be true, which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:133:51"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath; Leuiticall caeremonies were all ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of things to come.</p>
            <p>But ſay, I pray you, ſay ſoothely: doe you thinke Tythes were Leuiticall caeremonies if it be yeelded, that their payment in old Teſtament was remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of benefits receiued, and demonſtration of a praeſent thankfull minde? Thinke you all things done to God in remembrance of benefites receiued, in teſtimonie of a thankefull minde, Caeremonious, and Leuiticallie caeremonious? When <hi>Zachee</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that ſweete ſmelling ſacrifice,<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>halfe his goods to the poore,</hi> in part to demonſtrate preſent thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his late conuerſion, ſuppoſe you his fact a caeremonie, a Leuiticall caeremonie? when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of our forefathers, built Synagogues for our Nation, and erected Hoſpitals in remembrance of benefits receiued from God, ſuppoſe you their act Leuitically caeremonious? when <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> that is, not Poperie, but pore-blind deuotion, gaue Churches thoſe large endowments of lands and other reuenues which <hi>our Father,</hi> our more cleare-ſighted pietie hath ſtript them of, to rememorate priſtine bleſſings, and demonſtrate praeſent thankfulnes, can you thinke their fact therefore Leuitically caeremonious? This is my minde, in the maine of all my moralitie, its all by me done to rememorate paſt benefits, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate my praeſent thankfull minde; yet can I not bee perſwaded, I am herein Leuitically caeremonious. What then though it be granted, Tythes were paide by <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and in the whole time of old Teſtament in remembrance of benefits receiued, and to demonſtrate a thankfull minde praeſent; doth</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
